<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
  <doc>
    <field name="number">1</field>
    <field name="text" />
    <field name="text">ROBERT FULTON.</field>
    <field name="text">This story is about a giant.</field>
    <field name="text">Do you believe in them?</field>
    <field name="text">He peeps out of your coffee cup in the morning.</field>
    <field name="text">He cheers you upon a cold day in winter.</field>
    <field name="text">But the boys and girls were not so well acquainted with him a hundred years ago.</field>
    <field name="text">About that long ago, far to the north and east, a queer boy lived.</field>
    <field name="text">He sat in his grandmother's kitchen many an hour, watching the tea-kettle.</field>
    <field name="text">He seemed to be idle.</field>
    <field name="text">But he was really very busy.</field>
    <field name="text">He was talking very earnestly to the giant.</field>
    <field name="text">The giant was a prisoner.</field>
    <field name="text">No one knew how to free him.</field>
    <field name="text">Many had often tried to do this and failed.</field>
    <field name="text">He was almost always invisible.</field>
    <field name="text">But when he did appear, it was in the form of a very old man.</field>
    <field name="text">This old man had long, white hair, and a beard which seemed to enwrap him like a cloak--a cloak as white as snow.</field>
    <field name="text">So his name is The White Giant.</field>
    <field name="text">The boy's name was James Watt.</field>
    <field name="text">He lived in far-away Scotland.</field>
    <field name="text">He sat long, listening to the White Giant as he told him many wonderful things.</field>
    <field name="text">The way in which the giant first showed himself to James was very strange.</field>
    <field name="text">James noticed that the lid of the tea-kettle was acting very strangely.</field>
    <field name="text">It rose and fell, fluttered and danced.</field>
    <field name="text">Now, James had lived all his life among people who believed in witches and fairies.</field>
    <field name="text">So he was watching for them.</field>
    <field name="text">And he thought there was somebody in the kettle trying to get out.</field>
    <field name="text">So he said, "Who are you and what do you want?"</field>
    <field name="text">"Space, freedom, and something to do," cried the giant.</field>
    <field name="text">"If you will only let me out, I'll work hard for you.</field>
    <field name="text">I'll draw your carriages and ships.</field>
    <field name="text">I'll lift all your weights.</field>
    <field name="text">I'll turn all the wheels of your factories.</field>
    <field name="text">I'll be your servant always, in a thousand other ways."</field>
    <field name="text">[Illustration: JOHN FITCH'S STEAMBOAT, 1788.   By permission of Providence &amp; Stonington Steamship Co.]</field>
    <field name="text">If you have now guessed the common name of this giant, we will call him Steam.</field>
    <field name="text">At the time James Watt lived, there were no steam boats, steam mills, nor railways.</field>
    <field name="text">And this boy, though his grandmother scolded, thought much about the giant in the tea-kettle.</field>
    <field name="text">And he became the inventor of the first steam engine that was of any use to the world.</field>
    <field name="text">So, little by little, people came to know that steam is a great, good giant.</field>
    <field name="text">They tried in many different ways to make him useful.</field>
    <field name="text">They wished very much to make him run a boat.</field>
    <field name="text">One man tried to run his boat in a queer way.</field>
    <field name="text">He made something like a duck's foot to push it through the water.</field>
    <field name="text">Another moved his boat by forcing a stream of water in at the bow and out at the stern.</field>
    <field name="text">Then came a man named John Fitch.</field>
    <field name="text">He made his engine run a number of oars so as to paddle the boat forward.</field>
    <field name="text">He grew very poor.</field>
    <field name="text">People laughed at him.</field>
    <field name="text">But he said, "When I shall be forgotten, steam boats will run up the rivers and across the seas."</field>
    <field name="text">Then people laughed the harder and called him "a crank."</field>
    <field name="text">Mr. Fitch's boat was tried in 1787.</field>
    <field name="text">Now, in 1765, there happened a good thing for this old world.</field>
    <field name="text">A little baby boy was born in that year.</field>
    <field name="text">Perhaps you wonder why it was such a good thing for the world.</field>
    <field name="text">Some of you will know why when you read that this baby's name was Robert Fulton.</field>
    <field name="text">His father was poor.</field>
    <field name="text">His father was a farmer in Pennsylvania.</field>
    <field name="text">Mr. Fulton had two little girls older than baby Robert.</field>
    <field name="text">When Robert was grown larger he had three sisters and one brother.</field>
    <field name="text">But their father died when they were all small.</field>
    <field name="text">Robert did not go to school till he was eight years old.</field>
    <field name="text">His mother taught him at home.</field>
    <field name="text">He knew how to read and write, and a very little arithmetic.</field>
    <field name="text">His first teacher was a Mr. Johnson.</field>
    <field name="text">Mr. Johnson was a Quaker.</field>
    <field name="text">He thought Robert a dull pupil.</field>
    <field name="text">Robert did not learn his lessons very well.</field>
    <field name="text">But Mr. Johnson soon found that he was never idle.</field>
    <field name="text">He did not care to play at recess.</field>
    <field name="text">He stayed in and used his pencil in drawing.</field>
    <field name="text">He often spent hours in this way.</field>
    <field name="text">Robert soon became fond of going into the machine shops.</field>
    <field name="text">He understood machinery very quickly.</field>
    <field name="text">The men always gave him a welcome.</field>
    <field name="text">He didn't get into mischief.</field>
    <field name="text">He often helped the men with his neat drawings.</field>
    <field name="text">One day Robert was late in getting to school.</field>
    <field name="text">The master asked the reason.</field>
    <field name="text">Robert answered that he had been in Mr. Miller's shop pounding out lead for a lead pencil.</field>
    <field name="text">Mr. Johnson then encouraged him in doing such useful things.</field>
    <field name="text">In a few days, all the pupils in the school had pencils made in that way.</field>
    <field name="text">Mr. Johnson urged Robert to give more attention to his studies.</field>
    <field name="text">Robert said, "My head is so full of thoughts of my own that I haven't room there for the thoughts from dusty books."</field>
    <field name="text">As he was not idle, no doubt this was true.</field>
    <field name="text">When Robert was thirteen, the boys in the town had a great disappointment.</field>
    <field name="text">It was nearly July.</field>
    <field name="text">Of course the boys expected to celebrate the Fourth.</field>
    <field name="text">But a notice was put up.</field>
    <field name="text">This notice urged the people not to illuminate their homes.</field>
    <field name="text">It was very warm weather.</field>
    <field name="text">The people then had only candles with which to light their homes.</field>
    <field name="text">Candles were very scarce.</field>
    <field name="text">But Robert had some.</field>
    <field name="text">He took them to a shop and exchanged them for powder.</field>
    <field name="text">The owner of the store asked him why he gave up the candles, which were so scarce and dear.</field>
    <field name="text">Robert said, "I am a good citizen, and if our officers do not wish us to illuminate the town, I shall respect their wishes."</field>
    <field name="text">He found some pieces of paste-board.</field>
    <field name="text">He rolled these himself.</field>
    <field name="text">In this way he made some rockets.</field>
    <field name="text">The store-keeper told him he would find it impossible to do this.</field>
    <field name="text">"No, sir," Robert answered, "there is nothing impossible."</field>
    <field name="text">His rockets were a success, and the people were astonished.</field>
    <field name="text">Robert bought at different times small quantities of quicksilver.</field>
    <field name="text">The men in the machine shops were curious to know what he did with it.</field>
    <field name="text">But they could not find out.</field>
    <field name="text">For this reason they called him "Quicksilver Bob."</field>
    <field name="text">Robert was interested in guns.</field>
    <field name="text">Sometimes he would tell the workmen how to improve them.</field>
    <field name="text">The men liked him so well that they were always willing to try whatever he advised.</field>
    <field name="text">Robert was fond of fishing.</field>
    <field name="text">One of the workmen often went fishing with his father.</field>
    <field name="text">This man sometimes took Robert.</field>
    <field name="text">They had only an old flat boat.</field>
    <field name="text">The boys had to pole the boat from place to place.</field>
    <field name="text">It was hard work.</field>
    <field name="text">They were sometimes very tired.</field>
    <field name="text">Robert, soon after one fishing excursion, went away to visit an aunt.</field>
    <field name="text">He was gone a week.</field>
    <field name="text">While away he made a complete model of a little fishing boat.</field>
    <field name="text">This boat had paddle wheels.</field>
    <field name="text">The model was placed in the garret.</field>
    <field name="text">Many years afterward his aunt was proud to have it as an ornament on her parlor table.</field>
    <field name="text">Of course the boys arranged a set of paddle wheels for their fishing boat.</field>
    <field name="text">After this they enjoyed their fishing much more than before.</field>
    <field name="text">Robert Fulton's boyhood was during the Revolutionary War.</field>
    <field name="text">He made many queer pictures of the Hessian soldiers.</field>
    <field name="text">These Hessians were Germans, who had been hired by the British to help them fight the Americans.</field>
    <field name="text">The people who wished our country to belong to England were called Tories.</field>
    <field name="text">Those who wished America to be free were called Whigs.</field>
    <field name="text">The Whig boys often fought the Tory boys on the soldiers' camp ground.</field>
    <field name="text">The soldiers grew tired of this.</field>
    <field name="text">They stretched a rope to keep the boys out.</field>
    <field name="text">Robert drew a picture in which the Whigs crossed the rope and whipped the Tories.</field>
    <field name="text">The boys all thought it a good picture.</field>
    <field name="text">So they tried to make it real.</field>
    <field name="text">They became so troublesome that the town officers had to interfere.</field>
    <field name="text">But Robert was all this time fast growing up.</field>
    <field name="text">He had to choose some way of taking care of himself.</field>
    <field name="text">He was more fond of his pencil and brush than of anything else.</field>
    <field name="text">Near his home, had lived a celebrated painter.</field>
    <field name="text">His name was Benjamin West.</field>
    <field name="text">Benjamin West's father and Robert's father had been great friends.</field>
    <field name="text">Mr. West had become famous.</field>
    <field name="text">He now lived in England.</field>
    <field name="text">Robert thought he would like to be an artist, too.</field>
    <field name="text">So he left his home and went to the city of Philadelphia.</field>
    <field name="text">He knew that it meant hard work.</field>
    <field name="text">He was industrious and pains-taking.</field>
    <field name="text">He had many friends.</field>
    <field name="text">Benjamin Franklin was one of his friends.</field>
    <field name="text">Soon he did very nice work.</field>
    <field name="text">In the four years after he was seventeen, he not only took care of himself, but sent money to his mother and sisters.</field>
    <field name="text">He spent his twenty-first birthday at home.</field>
    <field name="text">He had then earned enough money to buy a small farm for his mother.</field>
    <field name="text">For this farm he paid four hundred dollars.</field>
    <field name="text">He helped his family to get nicely settled in their new home.</field>
    <field name="text">Then he went back to Philadelphia.</field>
    <field name="text">At this time Mr. Fulton, as we must now call him, was not well.</field>
    <field name="text">Partly for this reason he decided to take a voyage to Europe.</field>
    <field name="text">He carried letters from many well-known Americans.</field>
    <field name="text">He found friends in Europe.</field>
    <field name="text">Benjamin West was kind to him there.</field>
    <field name="text">[Illustration: A CANAL SCENE.]</field>
    <field name="text">He soon had plenty of work to do.</field>
    <field name="text">One of his friends was an English gentleman, who was called the Earl of Stanhope.</field>
    <field name="text">The Earl was much interested in canals.</field>
    <field name="text">Canals, you probably know, are artificial rivers.</field>
    <field name="text">Boats are drawn on them by horses, which walk along a path on the shore.</field>
    <field name="text">The path is called the tow-path.</field>
    <field name="text">Railways were almost unknown then.</field>
    <field name="text">So canals were very useful in carrying goods across the country.</field>
    <field name="text">They had been in use in Europe and Asia for hundreds of years.</field>
    <field name="text">Mr. Fulton invented a double inclined-plane.</field>
    <field name="text">This could be used in raising and lowering canal boats without disturbing their cargoes.</field>
    <field name="text">The British government gave Mr. Fulton a patent upon it.</field>
    <field name="text">Mr. Fulton wrote a book about canals and the ways in which they help a country.</field>
    <field name="text">He sent copies of this book to the President of the United States, and other men in high offices.</field>
    <field name="text">He thought canals would help America.</field>
    <field name="text">But it was ten years before he could get people to think much about it.</field>
    <field name="text">Then Mr. Fulton helped in planning the Erie Canal.</field>
    <field name="text">This was very successful.</field>
    <field name="text">You can see this canal now.</field>
    <field name="text">It is in the State of New York and is still used.</field>
    <field name="text">Mr. Fulton planned a cast-iron aqueduct which was built in Scotland.</field>
    <field name="text">An aqueduct is often made to carry water to cities.</field>
    <field name="text">He invented a mill for sawing marble, a machine for spinning flax, another for scooping out earth, called a dredging machine, and several kinds of canal boats.</field>
    <field name="text">You will wonder before reaching the end of this story how one man could do so many things.</field>
    <field name="text">But you must remember that he was never lazy as a boy, and so learned to make good use of every moment.</field>
    <field name="text">In 1797, Mr. Fulton went to the greatest city in France, called Paris.</field>
    <field name="text">There he made a new friend.</field>
    <field name="text">This was Joel Barlow, an American and a poet.</field>
    <field name="text">Mr. Fulton thought that all ships should have the freedom of the ocean.</field>
    <field name="text">He thought it would take hundreds of years to get all nations to consent to this.</field>
    <field name="text">He believed that he could find a quicker way.</field>
    <field name="text">He thought it would be best to blow up all warships.</field>
    <field name="text">He made a little sub-marine boat.</field>
    <field name="text">Sub-marine means under the sea.</field>
    <field name="text">This boat could be lowered below the surface of the water.</field>
    <field name="text">He found a way to supply it with air.</field>
    <field name="text">But he could not get it to run swiftly.</field>
    <field name="text">It took much money to build such boats.</field>
    <field name="text">He tried to get the French government to help him.</field>
    <field name="text">He was often tired and disappointed.</field>
    <field name="text">But he never stopped trying.</field>
    <field name="text">He tried to destroy some large boats.</field>
    <field name="text">This was to be done with torpedoes.</field>
    <field name="text">But he was not very successful.</field>
    <field name="text">He succeeded in destroying one boat.</field>
    <field name="text">But since then others have carried out his plan, and torpedoes are often used in war.</field>
    <field name="text">This little story is told of Mr. Fulton:--</field>
    <field name="text">He was once in New York working upon his torpedoes.</field>
    <field name="text">He invited the Mayor and many others to hear him lecture.</field>
    <field name="text">They came and were all much interested.</field>
    <field name="text">He showed them the copper cylinders which were to hold the powder.</field>
    <field name="text">Then he showed them the clockwork, which, when it was set running, would cause the cylinders to explode.</field>
    <field name="text">He turned to a case and drew out a peg.</field>
    <field name="text">He then said, "Gentlemen, this torpedo is all ready to blow up a vessel.</field>
    <field name="text">It contains one hundred and seventy pounds of powder.</field>
    <field name="text">The clockwork is now running.</field>
    <field name="text">If I should allow it to run fifteen minutes it would blow us all to atoms."</field>
    <field name="text">His audience was much frightened.</field>
    <field name="text">They all ran away.</field>
    <field name="text">Mr. Fulton put the peg back in its place.</field>
    <field name="text">He told them it was then safe.</field>
    <field name="text">Not until then did they dare come back.</field>
    <field name="text">But now our giant, Steam, became the friend of Mr. Fulton.</field>
    <field name="text">Many had tried to put this giant to work.</field>
    <field name="text">But at first he seemed rather hard to teach.</field>
    <field name="text">Long before, a poet had written these lines, which show how much people hoped to make the giant do:--</field>
    <field name="text">"Soon shall thy arm, unconquered Steam, afar     Drag the slow barge, or drive the rapid car."</field>
    <field name="text">It was a true prophecy.</field>
    <field name="text">Mr. Fulton married the daughter of a Mr. Walter Livingston.</field>
    <field name="text">This Mr. Livingston had a relative who was a great man, and a rich man.</field>
    <field name="text">He was much interested in all inventions.</field>
    <field name="text">He often helped inventors with his money.</field>
    <field name="text">He had long believed that boats could be moved by steam.</field>
    <field name="text">At one time the state of New York gave him the right of all steam boats for twenty years.</field>
    <field name="text">He was given the right if he would get one steam boat running within a year.</field>
    <field name="text">But the year passed and the boat was not built.</field>
    <field name="text">Everybody made fun of his "grand rights."</field>
    <field name="text">At this time our government made him our minister to France.</field>
    <field name="text">There he met Robert Fulton for the first time.</field>
    <field name="text">And in Paris Mr. Livingston and Mr. Fulton made a steam boat.</field>
    <field name="text">When it was finished they invited their friends to come and see it tried.</field>
    <field name="text">Early upon the morning when they hoped to succeed, a messenger came.</field>
    <field name="text">He bore sad news.</field>
    <field name="text">The new boat had broken in two.</field>
    <field name="text">The machinery was too heavy for it.</field>
    <field name="text">It had sunk to the bottom of the river Seine.</field>
    <field name="text">Mr. Fulton had not had his breakfast.</field>
    <field name="text">He hurried to the river.</field>
    <field name="text">He worked standing in the cold water.</field>
    <field name="text">In twenty-four hours he had saved the machinery, and some other parts of the boat.</field>
    <field name="text">But it made him ill.</field>
    <field name="text">He never was so strong again.</field>
    <field name="text">Of course he felt greatly discouraged.</field>
    <field name="text">They went to work again.</field>
    <field name="text">They built another boat.</field>
    <field name="text">This was a success.</field>
    <field name="text">It was sixty-six feet long, and moved by wheels on the side.</field>
    <field name="text">Mr. Livingston and Mr. Fulton decided to try again in America upon the Hudson River.</field>
    <field name="text">Mr. Livingston was given again the same privileges by the State of New York.</field>
    <field name="text">But this time Mr. Fulton was his partner.</field>
    <field name="text">They were given two years in which to make their boat.</field>
    <field name="text">They were to make one which could go four miles an hour.</field>
    <field name="text">It took much money.</field>
    <field name="text">Mr. Fulton promised to ask only a certain sum of Mr. Livingston.</field>
    <field name="text">But this sum proved to be too small.</field>
    <field name="text">He went to see a friend.</field>
    <field name="text">He talked long and earnestly to him.</field>
    <field name="text">But the friend grew tired and told him he must go home or go to bed.</field>
    <field name="text">Mr. Fulton wanted one thousand dollars.</field>
    <field name="text">His friend said he would see him again.</field>
    <field name="text">[Illustration: THE ERUCTOR AMPHIBOLIS.   A COMBINED STEAMBOAT AND LOCOMOTIVE CONSTRUCTED BY OLIVER EVANS   A NATIVE OF NEWPORT, DELAWARE, IN 1804.]</field>
    <field name="text">[Illustration: PERSPECTIVE VIEW OF MACHINERY IN FULTON'S   CLERMONT.   By permission of Providence &amp; Stonington Steamship Co.]</field>
    <field name="text">Mr. Fulton came again before the poor man had had any breakfast.</field>
    <field name="text">He gave him no peace.</field>
    <field name="text">But he got his money at last.</field>
    <field name="text">Mr. Fulton was much laughed at for trying to make such a boat.</field>
    <field name="text">The boat was called by people, "Fulton's Folly."</field>
    <field name="text">His friends would listen politely to him.</field>
    <field name="text">But he said he knew they did not believe in him.</field>
    <field name="text">He often, as he walked about, heard people laugh and sneer at him.</field>
    <field name="text">But at last the boat was done.</field>
    <field name="text">The sun rose smiling on that August morning.</field>
    <field name="text">The world was enjoying its morning nap.</field>
    <field name="text">Only a few people were on the shores.</field>
    <field name="text">Gracefully the boat was moved from the Jersey shore.</field>
    <field name="text">[Illustration: THE CLERMONT, 1807   By permission of Providence &amp; Stonington Steamship Co.]</field>
    <field name="text">Those who saw were amazed.</field>
    <field name="text">Old sailors were frightened.</field>
    <field name="text">When they saw a boat with no sails, they thought it an evil spirit.</field>
    <field name="text">But the long line of black smoke which they saw was only the breath of the dear old giant, Steam.</field>
    <field name="text">At last he had something to do.</field>
    <field name="text">This boat was called the Clermont.</field>
    <field name="text">It passed the city of New York.</field>
    <field name="text">It passed the beautiful Highlands of the Hudson.</field>
    <field name="text">It puffed patiently on until it reached Albany.</field>
    <field name="text">All along the shores people watched it breathlessly.</field>
    <field name="text">Everybody stopped sneering and cheered.</field>
    <field name="text">The Clermont had gone one hundred and fifty miles in thirty-two hours.</field>
    <field name="text">Except that the ocean steamships are larger, handsomer, and more finely finished, they are much like Mr. Fulton's Clermont.</field>
    <field name="text">Who can doubt Mr. Fulton's joy at his success.</field>
    <field name="text">At last he had found a way to make all nations know each other.</field>
    <field name="text">Mr. Fulton had other troubles after this.</field>
    <field name="text">Wicked people tried to steal his invention from him.</field>
    <field name="text">But no one else has ever been given credit for it.</field>
    <field name="text">Everyone who tried a ride upon the boat found it much nicer than jolting along in a stage coach.</field>
    <field name="text">In two years a regular line of boats was running between the great city of New York and its capital city.</field>
    <field name="text">Mr. Fulton built other boats.</field>
    <field name="text">Some of them were ferry-boats.</field>
    <field name="text">[Illustration: BROOKLYN BRIDGE AND FULTON FERRY.]</field>
    <field name="text">A ferry from New York to Long Island is still called by his name, Fulton Ferry.</field>
    <field name="text">Do you suppose the thousands of people who cross by it, ever think of patient, industrious, hard-working, Robert Fulton?</field>
    <field name="text">In January, 1815, Mr. Fulton went to Trenton, New Jersey, as witness in a lawsuit.</field>
    <field name="text">The weather was very severe.</field>
    <field name="text">Mr. Fulton became much chilled.</field>
    <field name="text">In coming back his boat was caught in the ice.</field>
    <field name="text">It was several hours before it could be moved.</field>
    <field name="text">You remember Mr. Fulton was not very strong.</field>
    <field name="text">He was ill for several days.</field>
    <field name="text">He was very anxious about a boat which he was building.</field>
    <field name="text">He left his bed too soon.</field>
    <field name="text">He was then taken very ill indeed.</field>
    <field name="text">And upon the twenty-fourth of February, 1815, the world lost this great man.</field>
    <field name="text">Everyone mourned his loss.</field>
    <field name="text">The great city of New York was in mourning.</field>
    <field name="text">He was buried in the Livingston vault in Trinity Churchyard, New York.</field>
    <field name="text">No monument has ever been raised over this great man.</field>
    <field name="text">But the boats which every year ply back and forth upon lake, river, and ocean, are constant reminders of his great work for the world.</field>
    <field name="text">[Illustration: ELI WHITNEY.]</field>
  </doc>
</add>
