<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
  <doc>
    <field name="number">5</field>
    <field name="text" />
    <field name="text">A GREAT INVENTOR.</field>
    <field name="text">Thomas A. Edison was born in Milan, Ohio, February 11, 1847.</field>
    <field name="text">There was nothing in Milan to make a boy wish to do great deeds.</field>
    <field name="text">There was a canal there.</field>
    <field name="text">Thomas had one great help--his mother.</field>
    <field name="text">She had been a teacher.</field>
    <field name="text">Her greatest wish for her son was that he should love knowledge.</field>
    <field name="text">Thomas had a quick mind.</field>
    <field name="text">He inquired into everything.</field>
    <field name="text">He was fond of getting every little thing well learned.</field>
    <field name="text">He never did things by halves.</field>
    <field name="text">He loved to try experiments.</field>
    <field name="text">When Thomas was a very little boy, only six years old, and still wearing dresses, he did a very funny thing.</field>
    <field name="text">He was one day found missing.</field>
    <field name="text">His frightened parents searched for him long and anxiously.</field>
    <field name="text">Where do you think he was found?</field>
    <field name="text">They found him in the barn, sitting on a nest of goose eggs, with his dress spread out to keep them warm.</field>
    <field name="text">He thought he could hatch some goslings as well as the mother-goose.</field>
    <field name="text">He had placed some food near by so that he might stay as long as necessary.</field>
    <field name="text">He went to a regular school only two months.</field>
    <field name="text">His father and mother were his teachers.</field>
    <field name="text">His father, to encourage him to read, paid him for every book which he read.</field>
    <field name="text">But Thomas did not need to be paid to read, for he read with pleasure every volume he could get hold of.</field>
    <field name="text">When he was ten years old, he was reading such books as Gibbon's "History of Rome," Hume's "History of England," and Sear's "History of the World."</field>
    <field name="text">Besides these, he had read several books about chemistry.</field>
    <field name="text">He loved to read about great men and their deeds.</field>
    <field name="text">When he played, it was at building plank roads, digging caves, and exploring the banks of the canal.</field>
    <field name="text">When only twelve years of age, he was obliged to go out into the world and earn his own living.</field>
    <field name="text">He obtained a place as train-boy on the Grand Trunk Railroad, in Eastern Michigan.</field>
    <field name="text">He sold apples, peanuts, song-books, and papers.</field>
    <field name="text">He had such a pleasant, sunny face that everyone liked to buy of him.</field>
    <field name="text">He succeeded so well that soon he had four boys working under him.</field>
    <field name="text">This was not enough to keep him busy.</field>
    <field name="text">He had never lost his liking for chemistry.</field>
    <field name="text">He managed to trade some of his papers for things with which to try experiments.</field>
    <field name="text">He found a book which helped him.</field>
    <field name="text">He fitted up an old baggage car as a room for his experiments.</field>
    <field name="text">He was afraid some one would touch his chemicals; so he labelled every bottle, "Poison."</field>
    <field name="text">Soon this busy boy had another business.</field>
    <field name="text">He bought three hundred pounds of old type from the "Detroit Free Press."</field>
    <field name="text">He had gained a little knowledge of printing by keeping his eyes open when buying papers.</field>
    <field name="text">Soon a paper, called the "Grand Trunk Herald," was printed by Master Tom.</field>
    <field name="text">This paper was twelve by sixteen inches in size.</field>
    <field name="text">It was filled with railway gossip and many other things of interest to travelers.</field>
    <field name="text">Baggagemen and brakemen wrote articles for it.</field>
    <field name="text">George Stephenson, who built a great bridge at Montreal, liked it so well that he ordered an extra edition for his own use.</field>
    <field name="text">Everybody liked it.</field>
    <field name="text">The "London Times" spoke of it as the only paper in the world published on a railway train.</field>
    <field name="text">But the "Grand Trunk Herald" had a sad ending.</field>
    <field name="text">Do you know what phosphorus is?</field>
    <field name="text">It is a substance which will take fire of itself if not kept under water.</field>
    <field name="text">Tom's bottle of phosphorus was thrown to the floor by the jolting of the car.</field>
    <field name="text">Soon everything was on fire.</field>
    <field name="text">The conductor rushed in and threw all the type and chemicals out of the car.</field>
    <field name="text">He also gave the young chemist a thrashing.</field>
    <field name="text">Poor Thomas gathered up what was left.</field>
    <field name="text">He put his things in the basement of his father's house.</field>
    <field name="text">Thomas's father now lived at Port Huron.</field>
    <field name="text">Thomas always slept at home.</field>
    <field name="text">He now printed another and a larger journal.</field>
    <field name="text">This was called the "Paul Pry."</field>
    <field name="text">In this he published an article which one of his subscribers did not like.</field>
    <field name="text">The angry man, meeting Thomas on the banks of the St. Clair River, picked him up and threw him in.</field>
    <field name="text">Thomas was a good swimmer and reached the shore in safety.</field>
    <field name="text">But he did not care for the printing business any more.</field>
    <field name="text">During the four years in which Thomas Edison was a train-boy, he had earned two thousand dollars and given it all to his parents.</field>
    <field name="text">When in Detroit, he read as much as possible from the public library.</field>
    <field name="text">Once he thought he would begin with number one and read each of the thousand volumes.</field>
    <field name="text">He read until he had finished a long row of hard books on a shelf fifteen feet long.</field>
    <field name="text">Then he made up his mind that anyone would have to live as long as Methuselah to read a library through, and gave up the plan.</field>
    <field name="text">Thomas became interested in telegraphy during the Civil War.</field>
    <field name="text">He used to telegraph the headings in his paper ahead one station.</field>
    <field name="text">He thought this a good way to advertise.</field>
    <field name="text">He finally bought a good book about electricity.</field>
    <field name="text">Soon the basement of the house at Port Huron was filled with many things beside printing presses.</field>
    <field name="text">He used stove-pipe wire, and soon had a telegraph wire between the basement and the home of a boy friend.</field>
    <field name="text">Perhaps it was a good thing that all the children in the Edison family were not like Thomas.</field>
    <field name="text">Had they been, the poor old house would scarcely have held them.</field>
    <field name="text">But the mother was proud of all that Thomas did.</field>
    <field name="text">She did not worry over the bottles, wires, strings, and printing presses.</field>
    <field name="text">About this time Thomas did a brave thing.</field>
    <field name="text">The station agent at Mt. Clemens had a baby boy two years old.</field>
    <field name="text">This baby crept on to the track in front of a train just coming in.</field>
    <field name="text">Quick as thought, young Edison rushed to the track and saved the child at the risk of his own life.</field>
    <field name="text">The baby's father was very grateful and offered to teach Thomas telegraphy.</field>
    <field name="text">Of course, Thomas was very happy, and accepted the offer.</field>
    <field name="text">He came to Mt. Clemens every evening, after working hard all day.</field>
    <field name="text">He did so well that, in five months, he was given a position at Port Huron.</field>
    <field name="text">He earned six and one-quarter dollars a week.</field>
    <field name="text">He worked almost night and day, so that he might learn all he could about it.</field>
    <field name="text">His mother said that the world would hear from her boy some day.</field>
    <field name="text">Afterwards he worked in several places.</field>
    <field name="text">In Indianapolis, though not yet seventeen, he invented his first telegraph instrument.</field>
    <field name="text">This was thought to be a great thing for so young a boy to do.</field>
    <field name="text">He lost several places because he tried new ways.</field>
    <field name="text">At last, he was obliged to walk nearly all the way to Louisville because he had no money.</field>
    <field name="text">Here he was given a good position.</field>
    <field name="text">He stayed several years.</field>
    <field name="text">Under the telegraph rooms was an elegant bank.</field>
    <field name="text">One day, while experimenting, he spilled a great bottle of acid.</field>
    <field name="text">This acid went through the floor into the bank below.</field>
    <field name="text">Of course it spoiled the ceiling, handsome carpets, and furniture.</field>
    <field name="text">So the unfortunate inventor had to leave Louisville.</field>
    <field name="text">He finally gave up trying to be a telegraph operator.</field>
    <field name="text">He opened a little shop.</field>
    <field name="text">He invented many things, and kept on thinking.</field>
    <field name="text">He could not make his inventions successful, for he had little money.</field>
    <field name="text">He thought so hard that he forgot everything else.</field>
    <field name="text">Once he was asked to speak before a company.</field>
    <field name="text">He forgot all about it.</field>
    <field name="text">They sent for him, and found him at the top of a house putting up a telegraph line.</field>
    <field name="text">He went in his working clothes to make his speech.</field>
    <field name="text">He felt queer when he found a room full of elegant ladies.</field>
    <field name="text">But he made a good speech.</field>
    <field name="text">Then he went to New York.</field>
    <field name="text">There he walked the streets three weeks, looking for work.</field>
    <field name="text">Nobody wanted a man who experimented.</field>
    <field name="text">By chance, he one day went into an office where the telegraph instrument was out of repair.</field>
    <field name="text">He offered to fix it.</field>
    <field name="text">They laughed at him, but let him try.</field>
    <field name="text">He succeeded in fixing it.</field>
    <field name="text">They gave him a good position.</field>
    <field name="text">From this time on there were better times for him.</field>
    <field name="text">After this the world soon sang his praises; and, in the next ten years, Fortune poured into his lap half a million dollars.</field>
    <field name="text">This was the result of his thinking.</field>
    <field name="text">The man who was in charge of the United States Patent Office called him "the young man who keeps the pathway to the Patent Office hot with his footsteps."</field>
    <field name="text">Mr. Edison believed that two messages could be sent over the same wire at the same time.</field>
    <field name="text">Of course the world laughed at the idea.</field>
    <field name="text">But soon our inventor managed to send four messages over the same wire at the same time.</field>
    <field name="text">Then the world stopped laughing.</field>
    <field name="text">People said, "This young man is the greatest inventor of his age, and a discoverer as well."</field>
    <field name="text">The Grand Trunk train-boy had proved a genius.</field>
    <field name="text">When twenty-six years of age, he married a young lady of Newark, Miss Mary Stillwell.</field>
    <field name="text">Three years later he moved to Menlo Park.</field>
    <field name="text">This was twenty-four miles from New York.</field>
    <field name="text">It was not a pleasant place, but he hoped to work there in quiet.</field>
    <field name="text">He had so many visitors that he could not work.</field>
    <field name="text">He said, "I think I shall fix a wire to my gate, and connect it with a battery so that it will knock everybody over that touches it."</field>
    <field name="text">But he was really kind.</field>
    <field name="text">He would smile pleasantly, and explain patiently to anyone who wished to know about his inventions.</field>
    <field name="text">At Menlo Park he built a great laboratory.</field>
    <field name="text">This was filled with batteries and machinery.</field>
    <field name="text">Here all the world came to see his wonderful talking machine.</field>
    <field name="text">It is called a phonograph.</field>
    <field name="text">What do you think Mr. Edison called this machine?</field>
    <field name="text">He said, "I have invented a great many machines, but this is my baby, and I expect it to grow up and support me in my old age."</field>
    <field name="text">Would you like to know the names of some of his inventions.</field>
    <field name="text">One is the carbon telephone.</field>
    <field name="text">The tasimeter measures the heat even of the far away stars.</field>
    <field name="text">The electric pen multiplies copies of letters and drawings.</field>
    <field name="text">Over sixty thousand are now in use in this country.</field>
    <field name="text">The automatic telegraph permits the sending of several thousand words over the same wire in one minute.</field>
    <field name="text">[Illustration]</field>
    <field name="text">There are many others.</field>
    <field name="text">Do you wonder that he is called "The Wizard of Menlo Park?"</field>
    <field name="text">But his crowning discovery is the electric light.</field>
    <field name="text">Some gentlemen of New York put one hundred thousand dollars into Mr. Edison's hands.</field>
    <field name="text">They told him to experiment until he could make a light which every one would be glad to use.</field>
    <field name="text">Many had tried to do this and had not succeeded.</field>
    <field name="text">It is said that he tried two thousand substances for the arch in his glass globe before he found one which suited him.</field>
    <field name="text">Do you know what he chose at last?</field>
    <field name="text">Do you remember the plant which the boys and girls of India, China, and Japan know so well?</field>
    <field name="text">It is the bamboo.</field>
    <field name="text">And it was bamboo which Mr. Edison chose.</field>
    <field name="text">Oh, how glad this light made many people!</field>
    <field name="text">In ten cotton factories in one town were men, women, and children working.</field>
    <field name="text">They worked in rooms where gas was used.</field>
    <field name="text">The gas injured their eyes and health.</field>
    <field name="text">Now in those same factories there are sixty thousand electric lights.</field>
    <field name="text">The bamboo burns six hundred hours before it has to be replaced.</field>
    <field name="text">Would you like a picture of Mr. Edison?</field>
    <field name="text">Close your eyes then and think of him like this.</field>
    <field name="text">He is five feet ten inches high.</field>
    <field name="text">His face is boyish, but earnest.</field>
    <field name="text">He has light gray eyes.</field>
    <field name="text">His hair is dark, slightly gray, and falls over his forehead.</field>
    <field name="text">He is a pleasant man to see.</field>
    <field name="text">He loves his work.</field>
    <field name="text">For ten years he has averaged eighteen hour's work a day.</field>
    <field name="text">You have seen that he is not a man to give up easily.</field>
    <field name="text">Once an invention of his--a printing press--failed.</field>
    <field name="text">He took five men into the upper part of his factory.</field>
    <field name="text">He declared he would never come down until it worked satisfactorily.</field>
    <field name="text">For two days and nights, and for twelve hours more, he worked without sleep.</field>
    <field name="text">He conquered the difficulty.</field>
    <field name="text">Then he slept thirty hours.</field>
    <field name="text">He often works all night.</field>
    <field name="text">He says he can work best when the rest of the world sleeps.</field>
    <field name="text">But he likes fun, too.</field>
    <field name="text">One day he said to his old friend, of whom he learned telegraphing,</field>
    <field name="text">"Look here--I am able to send a message from New York to Boston without any wire at all."</field>
    <field name="text">"That is impossible," said his friend.</field>
    <field name="text">"Oh, no, it's a new invention."</field>
    <field name="text">"Well, how is it done?" said Mr. McKensie.</field>
    <field name="text">"By sealing it up and sending by mail," was the comical answer.</field>
    <field name="text">He has two children.</field>
    <field name="text">One, a girl, Mary, is nicknamed "Dot."</field>
    <field name="text">The other, a son, Thomas, is called "Dash."</field>
    <field name="text">Mr. Edison doesn't like to have great dinners given in his honor.</field>
    <field name="text">But the world gives him great honors.</field>
    <field name="text">At the Paris Exposition in 1881, two great rooms were filled with his inventions.</field>
    <field name="text">The rooms were lighted with his lights.</field>
    <field name="text">He receives letters daily in French, German, Italian, Spanish, Russian, and Turkish.</field>
    <field name="text">Mr. Edison says, "Anything is possible with electricity."</field>
    <field name="text">That he is a genius, nobody can deny.</field>
    <field name="text">But do you suppose he could have done all these things without his great reading, or if he had been a lazy person?</field>
    <field name="text">*       *       *       *       *</field>
    <field name="text">+--------------------------------------------------------------+     | Typographical errors corrected in text:                      |     |                                                              |     | Page 141: perserverance replaced with perseverance           |     | Page 154: betwen replaced with between                       |     | Page 155: Clemans replaced with Clemens                      |     |                                                              |     +--------------------------------------------------------------+</field>
    <field name="text">*       *       *       *       *</field>
    <field name="text">End of Project Gutenberg's Stories of Great Inventors, by Hattie E. Macomber</field>
    <field name="text">*** END OF THIS PROJECT GUTENBERG EBOOK STORIES OF GREAT INVENTORS ***</field>
    <field name="text">***** This file should be named 19533.txt or 19533.zip ***** This and all associated files of various formats will be found in:         http://www.gutenberg.org/1/9/5/3/19533/</field>
    <field name="text">Produced by Juliet Sutherland, Jeannie Howse and the Online Distributed Proofreading Team at http://www.pgdp.net</field>
    <field name="text">Updated editions will replace the previous one--the old editions will be renamed.</field>
    <field name="text">Creating the works from public domain print editions means that no one owns a United States copyright in these works, so the Foundation (and you!) can copy and distribute it in the United States without permission and without paying copyright royalties.  Special rules, set forth in the General Terms of Use part of this license, apply to copying and distributing Project Gutenberg-tm electronic works to protect the PROJECT GUTENBERG-tm concept and trademark.  Project Gutenberg is a registered trademark, and may not be used if you charge for the eBooks, unless you receive specific permission.  If you do not charge anything for copies of this eBook, complying with the rules is very easy.  You may use this eBook for nearly any purpose such as creation of derivative works, reports, performances and research.  They may be modified and printed and given away--you may do practically ANYTHING with public domain eBooks.  Redistribution is subject to the trademark license, especially commercial redistribution.</field>
    <field name="text">*** START: FULL LICENSE ***</field>
    <field name="text">THE FULL PROJECT GUTENBERG LICENSE PLEASE READ THIS BEFORE YOU DISTRIBUTE OR USE THIS WORK</field>
    <field name="text">To protect the Project Gutenberg-tm mission of promoting the free distribution of electronic works, by using or distributing this work (or any other work associated in any way with the phrase "Project Gutenberg"), you agree to comply with all the terms of the Full Project Gutenberg-tm License (available with this file or online at http://gutenberg.org/license).</field>
    <field name="text">Section 1.  General Terms of Use and Redistributing Project Gutenberg-tm electronic works</field>
    <field name="text">1.A.  By reading or using any part of this Project Gutenberg-tm electronic work, you indicate that you have read, understand, agree to and accept all the terms of this license and intellectual property (trademark/copyright) agreement.  If you do not agree to abide by all the terms of this agreement, you must cease using and return or destroy all copies of Project Gutenberg-tm electronic works in your possession. If you paid a fee for obtaining a copy of or access to a Project Gutenberg-tm electronic work and you do not agree to be bound by the terms of this agreement, you may obtain a refund from the person or entity to whom you paid the fee as set forth in paragraph 1.E.8.</field>
    <field name="text">1.B.  "Project Gutenberg" is a registered trademark.  It may only be used on or associated in any way with an electronic work by people who agree to be bound by the terms of this agreement.  There are a few things that you can do with most Project Gutenberg-tm electronic works even without complying with the full terms of this agreement.  See paragraph 1.C below.  There are a lot of things you can do with Project Gutenberg-tm electronic works if you follow the terms of this agreement and help preserve free future access to Project Gutenberg-tm electronic works.  See paragraph 1.E below.</field>
    <field name="text">1.C.  The Project Gutenberg Literary Archive Foundation ("the Foundation" or PGLAF), owns a compilation copyright in the collection of Project Gutenberg-tm electronic works.  Nearly all the individual works in the collection are in the public domain in the United States.  If an individual work is in the public domain in the United States and you are located in the United States, we do not claim a right to prevent you from copying, distributing, performing, displaying or creating derivative works based on the work as long as all references to Project Gutenberg are removed.  Of course, we hope that you will support the Project Gutenberg-tm mission of promoting free access to electronic works by freely sharing Project Gutenberg-tm works in compliance with the terms of this agreement for keeping the Project Gutenberg-tm name associated with the work.  You can easily comply with the terms of this agreement by keeping this work in the same format with its attached full Project Gutenberg-tm License when you share it without charge with others.</field>
    <field name="text">1.D.  The copyright laws of the place where you are located also govern what you can do with this work.  Copyright laws in most countries are in a constant state of change.  If you are outside the United States, check the laws of your country in addition to the terms of this agreement before downloading, copying, displaying, performing, distributing or creating derivative works based on this work or any other Project Gutenberg-tm work.  The Foundation makes no representations concerning the copyright status of any work in any country outside the United States.</field>
    <field name="text">1.E.  Unless you have removed all references to Project Gutenberg:</field>
    <field name="text">1.E.1.  The following sentence, with active links to, or other immediate access to, the full Project Gutenberg-tm License must appear prominently whenever any copy of a Project Gutenberg-tm work (any work on which the phrase "Project Gutenberg" appears, or with which the phrase "Project Gutenberg" is associated) is accessed, displayed, performed, viewed, copied or distributed:</field>
    <field name="text">This eBook is for the use of anyone anywhere at no cost and with almost no restrictions whatsoever.  You may copy it, give it away or re-use it under the terms of the Project Gutenberg License included with this eBook or online at www.gutenberg.org</field>
    <field name="text">1.E.2.  If an individual Project Gutenberg-tm electronic work is derived from the public domain (does not contain a notice indicating that it is posted with permission of the copyright holder), the work can be copied and distributed to anyone in the United States without paying any fees or charges.  If you are redistributing or providing access to a work with the phrase "Project Gutenberg" associated with or appearing on the work, you must comply either with the requirements of paragraphs 1.E.1 through 1.E.7 or obtain permission for the use of the work and the Project Gutenberg-tm trademark as set forth in paragraphs 1.E.8 or 1.E.9.</field>
    <field name="text">1.E.3.  If an individual Project Gutenberg-tm electronic work is posted with the permission of the copyright holder, your use and distribution must comply with both paragraphs 1.E.1 through 1.E.7 and any additional terms imposed by the copyright holder.  Additional terms will be linked to the Project Gutenberg-tm License for all works posted with the permission of the copyright holder found at the beginning of this work.</field>
    <field name="text">1.E.4.  Do not unlink or detach or remove the full Project Gutenberg-tm License terms from this work, or any files containing a part of this work or any other work associated with Project Gutenberg-tm.</field>
    <field name="text">1.E.5.  Do not copy, display, perform, distribute or redistribute this electronic work, or any part of this electronic work, without prominently displaying the sentence set forth in paragraph 1.E.1 with active links or immediate access to the full terms of the Project Gutenberg-tm License.</field>
    <field name="text">1.E.6.  You may convert to and distribute this work in any binary, compressed, marked up, nonproprietary or proprietary form, including any word processing or hypertext form.  However, if you provide access to or distribute copies of a Project Gutenberg-tm work in a format other than "Plain Vanilla ASCII" or other format used in the official version posted on the official Project Gutenberg-tm web site (www.gutenberg.org), you must, at no additional cost, fee or expense to the user, provide a copy, a means of exporting a copy, or a means of obtaining a copy upon request, of the work in its original "Plain Vanilla ASCII" or other form.  Any alternate format must include the full Project Gutenberg-tm License as specified in paragraph 1.E.1.</field>
    <field name="text">1.E.7.  Do not charge a fee for access to, viewing, displaying, performing, copying or distributing any Project Gutenberg-tm works unless you comply with paragraph 1.E.8 or 1.E.9.</field>
    <field name="text">1.E.8.  You may charge a reasonable fee for copies of or providing access to or distributing Project Gutenberg-tm electronic works provided that</field>
    <field name="text">- You pay a royalty fee of 20% of the gross profits you derive from      the use of Project Gutenberg-tm works calculated using the method      you already use to calculate your applicable taxes.  The fee is      owed to the owner of the Project Gutenberg-tm trademark, but he      has agreed to donate royalties under this paragraph to the      Project Gutenberg Literary Archive Foundation.  Royalty payments      must be paid within 60 days following each date on which you      prepare (or are legally required to prepare) your periodic tax      returns.  Royalty payments should be clearly marked as such and      sent to the Project Gutenberg Literary Archive Foundation at the      address specified in Section 4, "Information about donations to      the Project Gutenberg Literary Archive Foundation."</field>
    <field name="text">- You provide a full refund of any money paid by a user who notifies      you in writing (or by e-mail) within 30 days of receipt that s/he      does not agree to the terms of the full Project Gutenberg-tm      License.  You must require such a user to return or      destroy all copies of the works possessed in a physical medium      and discontinue all use of and all access to other copies of      Project Gutenberg-tm works.</field>
    <field name="text">- You provide, in accordance with paragraph 1.F.3, a full refund of any      money paid for a work or a replacement copy, if a defect in the      electronic work is discovered and reported to you within 90 days      of receipt of the work.</field>
    <field name="text">- You comply with all other terms of this agreement for free      distribution of Project Gutenberg-tm works.</field>
    <field name="text">1.E.9.  If you wish to charge a fee or distribute a Project Gutenberg-tm electronic work or group of works on different terms than are set forth in this agreement, you must obtain permission in writing from both the Project Gutenberg Literary Archive Foundation and Michael Hart, the owner of the Project Gutenberg-tm trademark.  Contact the Foundation as set forth in Section 3 below.</field>
    <field name="text">1.F.</field>
    <field name="text">1.F.1.  Project Gutenberg volunteers and employees expend considerable effort to identify, do copyright research on, transcribe and proofread public domain works in creating the Project Gutenberg-tm collection.  Despite these efforts, Project Gutenberg-tm electronic works, and the medium on which they may be stored, may contain "Defects," such as, but not limited to, incomplete, inaccurate or corrupt data, transcription errors, a copyright or other intellectual property infringement, a defective or damaged disk or other medium, a computer virus, or computer codes that damage or cannot be read by your equipment.</field>
    <field name="text">1.F.2.  LIMITED WARRANTY, DISCLAIMER OF DAMAGES - Except for the "Right of Replacement or Refund" described in paragraph 1.F.3, the Project Gutenberg Literary Archive Foundation, the owner of the Project Gutenberg-tm trademark, and any other party distributing a Project Gutenberg-tm electronic work under this agreement, disclaim all liability to you for damages, costs and expenses, including legal fees.  YOU AGREE THAT YOU HAVE NO REMEDIES FOR NEGLIGENCE, STRICT LIABILITY, BREACH OF WARRANTY OR BREACH OF CONTRACT EXCEPT THOSE PROVIDED IN PARAGRAPH F3.  YOU AGREE THAT THE FOUNDATION, THE TRADEMARK OWNER, AND ANY DISTRIBUTOR UNDER THIS AGREEMENT WILL NOT BE LIABLE TO YOU FOR ACTUAL, DIRECT, INDIRECT, CONSEQUENTIAL, PUNITIVE OR INCIDENTAL DAMAGES EVEN IF YOU GIVE NOTICE OF THE POSSIBILITY OF SUCH DAMAGE.</field>
    <field name="text">1.F.3.  LIMITED RIGHT OF REPLACEMENT OR REFUND - If you discover a defect in this electronic work within 90 days of receiving it, you can receive a refund of the money (if any) you paid for it by sending a written explanation to the person you received the work from.  If you received the work on a physical medium, you must return the medium with your written explanation.  The person or entity that provided you with the defective work may elect to provide a replacement copy in lieu of a refund.  If you received the work electronically, the person or entity providing it to you may choose to give you a second opportunity to receive the work electronically in lieu of a refund.  If the second copy is also defective, you may demand a refund in writing without further opportunities to fix the problem.</field>
    <field name="text">1.F.4.  Except for the limited right of replacement or refund set forth in paragraph 1.F.3, this work is provided to you 'AS-IS' WITH NO OTHER WARRANTIES OF ANY KIND, EXPRESS OR IMPLIED, INCLUDING BUT NOT LIMITED TO WARRANTIES OF MERCHANTIBILITY OR FITNESS FOR ANY PURPOSE.</field>
    <field name="text">1.F.5.  Some states do not allow disclaimers of certain implied warranties or the exclusion or limitation of certain types of damages. If any disclaimer or limitation set forth in this agreement violates the law of the state applicable to this agreement, the agreement shall be interpreted to make the maximum disclaimer or limitation permitted by the applicable state law.  The invalidity or unenforceability of any provision of this agreement shall not void the remaining provisions.</field>
    <field name="text">1.F.6.  INDEMNITY - You agree to indemnify and hold the Foundation, the trademark owner, any agent or employee of the Foundation, anyone providing copies of Project Gutenberg-tm electronic works in accordance with this agreement, and any volunteers associated with the production, promotion and distribution of Project Gutenberg-tm electronic works, harmless from all liability, costs and expenses, including legal fees, that arise directly or indirectly from any of the following which you do or cause to occur: (a) distribution of this or any Project Gutenberg-tm work, (b) alteration, modification, or additions or deletions to any Project Gutenberg-tm work, and (c) any Defect you cause.</field>
    <field name="text">Section  2.  Information about the Mission of Project Gutenberg-tm</field>
    <field name="text">Project Gutenberg-tm is synonymous with the free distribution of electronic works in formats readable by the widest variety of computers including obsolete, old, middle-aged and new computers.  It exists because of the efforts of hundreds of volunteers and donations from people in all walks of life.</field>
    <field name="text">Volunteers and financial support to provide volunteers with the assistance they need, is critical to reaching Project Gutenberg-tm's goals and ensuring that the Project Gutenberg-tm collection will remain freely available for generations to come.  In 2001, the Project Gutenberg Literary Archive Foundation was created to provide a secure and permanent future for Project Gutenberg-tm and future generations. To learn more about the Project Gutenberg Literary Archive Foundation and how your efforts and donations can help, see Sections 3 and 4 and the Foundation web page at http://www.pglaf.org.</field>
    <field name="text">Section 3.  Information about the Project Gutenberg Literary Archive Foundation</field>
    <field name="text">The Project Gutenberg Literary Archive Foundation is a non profit 501(c)(3) educational corporation organized under the laws of the state of Mississippi and granted tax exempt status by the Internal Revenue Service.  The Foundation's EIN or federal tax identification number is 64-6221541.  Its 501(c)(3) letter is posted at http://pglaf.org/fundraising.  Contributions to the Project Gutenberg Literary Archive Foundation are tax deductible to the full extent permitted by U.S. federal laws and your state's laws.</field>
    <field name="text">The Foundation's principal office is located at 4557 Melan Dr. S. Fairbanks, AK, 99712., but its volunteers and employees are scattered throughout numerous locations.  Its business office is located at 809 North 1500 West, Salt Lake City, UT 84116, (801) 596-1887, email business@pglaf.org.  Email contact links and up to date contact information can be found at the Foundation's web site and official page at http://pglaf.org</field>
    <field name="text">For additional contact information:      Dr. Gregory B. Newby      Chief Executive and Director      gbnewby@pglaf.org</field>
    <field name="text">Section 4.  Information about Donations to the Project Gutenberg Literary Archive Foundation</field>
    <field name="text">Project Gutenberg-tm depends upon and cannot survive without wide spread public support and donations to carry out its mission of increasing the number of public domain and licensed works that can be freely distributed in machine readable form accessible by the widest array of equipment including outdated equipment.  Many small donations ($1 to $5,000) are particularly important to maintaining tax exempt status with the IRS.</field>
    <field name="text">The Foundation is committed to complying with the laws regulating charities and charitable donations in all 50 states of the United States.  Compliance requirements are not uniform and it takes a considerable effort, much paperwork and many fees to meet and keep up with these requirements.  We do not solicit donations in locations where we have not received written confirmation of compliance.  To SEND DONATIONS or determine the status of compliance for any particular state visit http://pglaf.org</field>
    <field name="text">While we cannot and do not solicit contributions from states where we have not met the solicitation requirements, we know of no prohibition against accepting unsolicited donations from donors in such states who approach us with offers to donate.</field>
    <field name="text">International donations are gratefully accepted, but we cannot make any statements concerning tax treatment of donations received from outside the United States.  U.S. laws alone swamp our small staff.</field>
    <field name="text">Please check the Project Gutenberg Web pages for current donation methods and addresses.  Donations are accepted in a number of other ways including checks, online payments and credit card donations. To donate, please visit: http://pglaf.org/donate</field>
    <field name="text">Section 5.  General Information About Project Gutenberg-tm electronic works.</field>
    <field name="text">Professor Michael S. Hart is the originator of the Project Gutenberg-tm concept of a library of electronic works that could be freely shared with anyone.  For thirty years, he produced and distributed Project Gutenberg-tm eBooks with only a loose network of volunteer support.</field>
    <field name="text">Project Gutenberg-tm eBooks are often created from several printed editions, all of which are confirmed as Public Domain in the U.S. unless a copyright notice is included.  Thus, we do not necessarily keep eBooks in compliance with any particular paper edition.</field>
    <field name="text">Most people start at our Web site which has the main PG search facility:</field>
    <field name="text">http://www.gutenberg.org</field>
    <field name="text">This Web site includes information about Project Gutenberg-tm, including how to make donations to the Project Gutenberg Literary Archive Foundation, how to help produce our new eBooks, and how to subscribe to our email newsletter to hear about new eBooks.</field>
  </doc>
</add>
