<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
  <doc>
    <field name="number">2</field>
    <field name="text" />
    <field name="text">ELI WHITNEY.</field>
    <field name="text">The war, called the Revolution, was ended.</field>
    <field name="text">The treaty of peace had been signed.</field>
    <field name="text">America had won her freedom.</field>
    <field name="text">Our country then was smaller than now.</field>
    <field name="text">It contained only about four million people.</field>
    <field name="text">These people were widely scattered.</field>
    <field name="text">The world did not think of the United States as an important country.</field>
    <field name="text">It was thought to be about as important as Denmark or Portugal is now.</field>
    <field name="text">We call one part of our country the South.</field>
    <field name="text">The South of this time was very different from the South of to-day.</field>
    <field name="text">Fewer cities were to be seen.</field>
    <field name="text">Many forests covered the land.</field>
    <field name="text">The plantations were few.</field>
    <field name="text">Plantation is the southern word for farm.</field>
    <field name="text">There were not many slaves then.</field>
    <field name="text">People hoped slavery would die out.</field>
    <field name="text">They thought it might if it were let alone.</field>
    <field name="text">Many people left the South to find other homes.</field>
    <field name="text">This was because they could not make a good living there.</field>
    <field name="text">Indigo, rice, and cotton were raised.</field>
    <field name="text">But only a little cotton was planted.</field>
    <field name="text">This was because it was such hard work to get it ready to sell.</field>
    <field name="text">Cotton grows upon a small shrub.</field>
    <field name="text">People of olden times called it the "wool of trees."</field>
    <field name="text">The Germans still call it "tree-wool."</field>
    <field name="text">One kind is called "sea-island" cotton.</field>
    <field name="text">This is because it grows well upon the low, sandy islands of the sea.</field>
    <field name="text">Some such islands are found near South Carolina.</field>
    <field name="text">This cotton likes the salt which it finds in the soil.</field>
    <field name="text">The herb cotton grows to a height of from eighteen to twenty-four inches.</field>
    <field name="text">The land is made ready for the seed during the winter.</field>
    <field name="text">As soon as the frost is gone Mother Earth is given her baby seeds to care for.</field>
    <field name="text">Soon the beautiful plantlets appear.</field>
    <field name="text">The leaves are of a dark green.</field>
    <field name="text">Then later come the pale yellow flowers.</field>
    <field name="text">The plants must then be well cared for.</field>
    <field name="text">Toward autumn the fruit is seen.</field>
    <field name="text">This looks like a walnut still in its rough coat.</field>
    <field name="text">[Illustration: COTTON BALLS.]</field>
    <field name="text">Then the pods burst.</field>
    <field name="text">The field is then beautiful.</field>
    <field name="text">It looks as if it were covered with snow.</field>
    <field name="text">Then comes the hard work of the picking.</field>
    <field name="text">All hands upon the plantation must then work in the fields.</field>
    <field name="text">The slaves of long ago were kept very busy during this season.</field>
    <field name="text">The women and children worked.</field>
    <field name="text">They have to be careful that the cotton is quite dry when picked.</field>
    <field name="text">If it were damp the cotton would mould.</field>
    <field name="text">This would spoil it for use.</field>
    <field name="text">Can you imagine a snow-white field dotted with black people?</field>
    <field name="text">Their bright eyes must have shone still more brightly there.</field>
    <field name="text">The cotton does not all ripen at one time.</field>
    <field name="text">But it must be gathered soon after the pods are burst.</field>
    <field name="text">[Illustration]</field>
    <field name="text">This is because the sun injures the color of the cotton.</field>
    <field name="text">Or the rain and dews injure it.</field>
    <field name="text">Or the winds may blow it away.</field>
    <field name="text">So the cotton pickers were kept busy from August until the frost came.</field>
    <field name="text">They went over the same fields many times.</field>
    <field name="text">Then, after a busy day in the field, other work remained to be done.</field>
    <field name="text">The cotton pickers sat upon the ground in a circle.</field>
    <field name="text">From the midst of the cotton they took the black seeds.</field>
    <field name="text">These seeds were very troublesome.</field>
    <field name="text">They are covered with hairs.</field>
    <field name="text">They cling fast to the cotton.</field>
    <field name="text">These naughty children of the plant love their mother.</field>
    <field name="text">So fast do they cling to her, that a person could clean but one pound of cotton in a whole day.</field>
    <field name="text">So you may understand why so little was raised.</field>
    <field name="text">In 1784, eight bags of cotton were taken from the United States to England.</field>
    <field name="text">These were seized by the custom officers.</field>
    <field name="text">These officers are those who look after goods sent in or out of a country.</field>
    <field name="text">If money is to be paid upon the goods, it is called a duty.</field>
    <field name="text">The custom officers must see that the duty is paid.</field>
    <field name="text">These men said that this cotton could not have come from America.</field>
    <field name="text">During the next two years less than one hundred-twenty bags were sent there from our country.</field>
    <field name="text">The treaty of peace with England was made in 1794.</field>
    <field name="text">None of the treaty-makers then knew that any cotton was raised in America.</field>
    <field name="text">Would you like to know why, fifty years later, a million bales were sent from America?</field>
    <field name="text">This is the story:</field>
    <field name="text">In the war with England, America had some brave generals.</field>
    <field name="text">One of these was General Nathaniel Greene.</field>
    <field name="text">He had helped to win victories in the South.</field>
    <field name="text">The State of Georgia gave him a tract of land.</field>
    <field name="text">General Greene lived with his family upon this land.</field>
    <field name="text">He at last died there.</field>
    <field name="text">Mrs. Greene was very lonely.</field>
    <field name="text">She went to the North to visit her friends.</field>
    <field name="text">On her voyage home she met a pleasant gentleman.</field>
    <field name="text">He was a young man, only twenty-seven years of age.</field>
    <field name="text">He, too, was going to Georgia.</field>
    <field name="text">His name was Eli Whitney.</field>
    <field name="text">And now you must know something of his story.</field>
    <field name="text">Eli Whitney was born in Massachusetts in 1765.</field>
    <field name="text">His people were farmers.</field>
    <field name="text">They were not rich people.</field>
    <field name="text">Eli's father had a workshop.</field>
    <field name="text">In this shop he worked upon rainy days.</field>
    <field name="text">He made wheels and chairs.</field>
    <field name="text">Eli grew up like other farm boys.</field>
    <field name="text">He helped on the farm.</field>
    <field name="text">He attended the district school.</field>
    <field name="text">He took care of the cattle and horses.</field>
    <field name="text">But very early in his life he became fond of tools.</field>
    <field name="text">He used to creep into his father's shop.</field>
    <field name="text">He could scarcely wait to be old enough to use the tools there.</field>
    <field name="text">One of the interesting tools was a lathe for turning chair posts.</field>
    <field name="text">His father allowed him the use of all these as soon as he was large enough to take care of them.</field>
    <field name="text">After that, he was always at work at something.</field>
    <field name="text">He liked work in the shop much more than work upon the farm.</field>
    <field name="text">Eli's mother died when he was a little boy.</field>
    <field name="text">This is a sad event in any boy's life.</field>
    <field name="text">When Eli was about twelve years old, his father took a journey from home.</field>
    <field name="text">He was gone two or three days.</field>
    <field name="text">When he returned, he called the housekeeper.</field>
    <field name="text">He asked her what the boys had been doing.</field>
    <field name="text">She told him what the elder boys had done.</field>
    <field name="text">"But what has Eli been doing?" said he.</field>
    <field name="text">"He has been making a fiddle," was the answer.</field>
    <field name="text">"Ah!" said the father, "I fear Eli will take his portion in fiddles."</field>
    <field name="text">The fiddle was finished like a common violin.</field>
    <field name="text">It made pretty good music.</field>
    <field name="text">Many people came to see it.</field>
    <field name="text">They said it was a fine piece of work for a boy.</field>
    <field name="text">Afterwards people brought him their violins to mend.</field>
    <field name="text">He did the mending nicely.</field>
    <field name="text">Every one was surprised.</field>
    <field name="text">They brought him other work to do.</field>
    <field name="text">Eli's father had a nice watch.</field>
    <field name="text">Eli loved to look at it.</field>
    <field name="text">It was a great wonder to him.</field>
    <field name="text">He wished to see the inside of it.</field>
    <field name="text">His father would not allow this.</field>
    <field name="text">One Sunday the family were getting ready for church.</field>
    <field name="text">Eli noticed that his father intended leaving his watch at home.</field>
    <field name="text">He could not lose such a good chance.</field>
    <field name="text">So he pretended to be quite sick.</field>
    <field name="text">His father allowed him to stay at home.</field>
    <field name="text">Soon he was alone with the wonderful little watch.</field>
    <field name="text">He hurried to the room where it hung.</field>
    <field name="text">He took it down carefully.</field>
    <field name="text">His hands shook, but he managed to open it.</field>
    <field name="text">How delightful was the motion of those wheels!</field>
    <field name="text">It seemed a living thing.</field>
    <field name="text">Eli forgot his father.</field>
    <field name="text">He thought only of the wonderful machinery.</field>
    <field name="text">He must know just how it went.</field>
    <field name="text">He took the watch all to pieces before he remembered how wrong it was to do so.</field>
    <field name="text">Then he began to be frightened.</field>
    <field name="text">What if he couldn't put it together!</field>
    <field name="text">He knew his father was a very stern man.</field>
    <field name="text">Slowly and carefully the boy went to work.</field>
    <field name="text">And so bright was he that he succeeded in getting it together all right.</field>
    <field name="text">His father did not find out the mischief.</field>
    <field name="text">Several years afterward Eli told him about it.</field>
    <field name="text">When Eli was thirteen years old his father married a second time.</field>
    <field name="text">Eli's stepmother had a handsome set of table knives.</field>
    <field name="text">She valued them highly.</field>
    <field name="text">One day Eli said, "I could make as good knives as those if I had tools.</field>
    <field name="text">"And I could make the tools if I had common tools to begin with."</field>
    <field name="text">His mother laughed at him.</field>
    <field name="text">But soon after one of the knives was broken.</field>
    <field name="text">Eli made a blade exactly like the broken one, except its stamp.</field>
    <field name="text">Soon Eli was fifteen years of age.</field>
    <field name="text">He wished to go into the nail-making business.</field>
    <field name="text">It was during the Revolution.</field>
    <field name="text">Nails were made almost entirely by hand.</field>
    <field name="text">They were in great demand.</field>
    <field name="text">They brought good prices.</field>
    <field name="text">Eli asked his father to bring him a few tools.</field>
    <field name="text">His father consented.</field>
    <field name="text">The work was begun.</field>
    <field name="text">Eli was very industrious.</field>
    <field name="text">He made good nails.</field>
    <field name="text">He also found time to make more tools for his own use.</field>
    <field name="text">He put in knife blades.</field>
    <field name="text">He repaired broken machinery.</field>
    <field name="text">He did many other things beyond the skill of country workmen.</field>
    <field name="text">Eli worked in this way two winters.</field>
    <field name="text">He made money.</field>
    <field name="text">He worked on the farm in the summer.</field>
    <field name="text">At one time Eli took a journey of forty miles.</field>
    <field name="text">He visited every workshop on the way.</field>
    <field name="text">These visits taught him much.</field>
    <field name="text">He found a man who could go back with him and help him in his business.</field>
    <field name="text">At the close of the war it did not pay to go on with the nail-making.</field>
    <field name="text">The ladies began a new fashion about that time.</field>
    <field name="text">This was the use of long pins for fastening on their bonnets.</field>
    <field name="text">He made very nearly all the pins used.</field>
    <field name="text">Eli made these pins with great skill.</field>
    <field name="text">This work was done in the time spared from his farm work.</field>
    <field name="text">He also made excellent walking canes.</field>
    <field name="text">During all these years Eli's schooling had been received at different times at the district school.</field>
    <field name="text">He was very fond of arithmetic.</field>
    <field name="text">During his nineteenth year he made up his mind to have a college education.</field>
    <field name="text">His step-mother did not wish him to do this.</field>
    <field name="text">But he worked hard and saved his money.</field>
    <field name="text">A part of the time he taught school.</field>
    <field name="text">He was twenty-three when he entered Yale College.</field>
    <field name="text">He borrowed some money, for which he gave his note.</field>
    <field name="text">At one time one of the college teachers wished to show his pupils some experiments. But some of the things to be used were broken.</field>
    <field name="text">Eli offered to mend them.</field>
    <field name="text">This he did, and succeeded in surprising every one.</field>
    <field name="text">A carpenter lived near his boarding place.</field>
    <field name="text">Eli asked for the loan of some of his tools.</field>
    <field name="text">The careful carpenter did not wish to lend them.</field>
    <field name="text">He at last gave his consent in this way:--</field>
    <field name="text">The gentleman with whom Mr. Whitney boarded must promise to pay all the damages.</field>
    <field name="text">But he soon saw how skilful Mr. Whitney was.</field>
    <field name="text">He was surprised and said:</field>
    <field name="text">"There was one good mechanic spoiled when you went to college."</field>
    <field name="text">Mr. Whitney graduated in 1792.</field>
    <field name="text">He was engaged by a gentleman in Georgia to teach his children.</field>
    <field name="text">It was on this journey to his new work that he met Mrs. Greene.</field>
    <field name="text">Mrs. Greene liked Mr. Whitney very much.</field>
    <field name="text">When they reached Savannah, she invited him to her home.</field>
    <field name="text">At this time he had a great disappointment.</field>
    <field name="text">The gentleman who had hired him to come to Georgia coolly told him his services were not wanted.</field>
    <field name="text">He had no friends.</field>
    <field name="text">He was out of money.</field>
    <field name="text">But Mrs. Greene became his good friend.</field>
    <field name="text">He went to live at her house.</field>
    <field name="text">Here he began the study of law.</field>
    <field name="text">Mrs. Greene was one day doing some embroidery.</field>
    <field name="text">She broke the frame upon which she was working.</field>
    <field name="text">She did not know how to finish the work without it.</field>
    <field name="text">Mr. Whitney looked at it carefully.</field>
    <field name="text">Then he made her a new frame.</field>
    <field name="text">It was even better than the other one had been.</field>
    <field name="text">Of course Mrs. Greene was much pleased.</field>
    <field name="text">Mr. Whitney also made fine toys for the children.</field>
    <field name="text">Soon after this, a party of gentlemen visited at Mrs. Greene's home.</field>
    <field name="text">They were nearly all men who had been officers during the war.</field>
    <field name="text">Mr. Greene had been their general.</field>
    <field name="text">They began talking of the South.</field>
    <field name="text">They wished something might be done to improve that part of the country.</field>
    <field name="text">They wished it might be made a better place in which to live.</field>
    <field name="text">They spoke of the fine spinning machines that were coming into use in England.</field>
    <field name="text">Much land in the South could be used for cotton.</field>
    <field name="text">This could be sent to England for manufacture.</field>
    <field name="text">The South could become a rich country in this way.</field>
    <field name="text">But there was one great difficulty.</field>
    <field name="text">It cost so much to clean the cotton.</field>
    <field name="text">Mrs. Greene said, "I know who can help you.</field>
    <field name="text">"Apply to my young friend, Mr. Whitney. He can make anything."</field>
    <field name="text">She then showed the gentlemen her frame and other things which Mr. Whitney had made.</field>
    <field name="text">Mr. Whitney said he had never seen cotton or its seed.</field>
    <field name="text">None was raised near the home of the Greene's.</field>
    <field name="text">Mr. Whitney did not make any promises.</field>
    <field name="text">But the next day he went to work.</field>
    <field name="text">He went first to the city of Savannah.</field>
    <field name="text">There he searched among the warehouses and boats.</field>
    <field name="text">At last he found a small parcel of cotton.</field>
    <field name="text">This he carried home.</field>
    <field name="text">He shut himself up in a small basement room.</field>
    <field name="text">His tools were poor.</field>
    <field name="text">He made better ones.</field>
    <field name="text">No wire could be bought in Savannah.</field>
    <field name="text">So he made his own wire.</field>
    <field name="text">Mrs. Greene and a Mr. Miller were the only persons allowed to come into his work-shop.</field>
    <field name="text">Day after day the children wondered to hear the queer clinking and hammering.</field>
    <field name="text">They laughed at Mr. Whitney.</field>
    <field name="text">But that did not trouble him.</field>
    <field name="text">Before the end of the winter the machine was nearly perfect.</field>
    <field name="text">Its success seemed certain.</field>
    <field name="text">Mrs. Greene was very happy over the work.</field>
    <field name="text">She was eager that people should know about this wonderful invention.</field>
    <field name="text">She could not wait until a patent was secured.</field>
    <field name="text">A patent is given by the government.</field>
    <field name="text">It is given to prevent others from claiming an invention.</field>
    <field name="text">Often it keeps people from manufacturing the article without the permission of the owner.</field>
    <field name="text">So Mrs. Green invited a party of gentlemen from all parts of the state to visit her.</field>
    <field name="text">These gentlemen were taken to see the machine do its work.</field>
    <field name="text">They were greatly astonished.</field>
    <field name="text">For what did they see?</field>
    <field name="text">This curious little machine cleaned the cotton of its seed.</field>
    <field name="text">And it would clean in a day more than a man could do in months.</field>
    <field name="text">They went to their homes.</field>
    <field name="text">They told everybody about it.</field>
    <field name="text">Great crowds began coming to see it.</field>
    <field name="text">But they were refused permission to do so.</field>
    <field name="text">This was because it had not yet been patented.</field>
    <field name="text">So one night some wicked men broke into the building.</field>
    <field name="text">They stole the cotton-gin.</field>
    <field name="text">You can well imagine how dreadful this was.</field>
    <field name="text">Mr. Whitney had no money.</field>
    <field name="text">So Mr. Miller agreed to be his partner.</field>
    <field name="text">Mr. Miller had come to Georgia from the North.</field>
    <field name="text">He, too, was a graduate of Yale College.</field>
    <field name="text">He afterward married Mrs. Greene.</field>
    <field name="text">He became Mr. Whitney's partner in May, 1773.</field>
    <field name="text">Perhaps you wonder why the machine was called a gin. It was a short way of saying engine.</field>
    <field name="text">A gin is a machine that aids the work of a person.</field>
    <field name="text">The cotton-gin was made to work much the same as the hand of a person.</field>
    <field name="text">It dragged the cotton away from the seed.</field>
    <field name="text">And now begins the sorrowful part of the story.</field>
    <field name="text">Before Mr. Whitney could get his patent, several other gins had been made.</field>
    <field name="text">Each claimed to be the best.</field>
    <field name="text">The plans were all stolen from Mr. Whitney's.</field>
    <field name="text">[Illustration: ROLLER-GIN.]</field>
    <field name="text">One was the roller-gin.</field>
    <field name="text">This crushed the seed in the cotton.</field>
    <field name="text">Of course this injured the cotton.</field>
    <field name="text">Another was the saw-gin.</field>
    <field name="text">This was exactly like Mr. Whitney's, except that the saws were set differently.</field>
    <field name="text">Many lawsuits were begun.</field>
    <field name="text">Mr. Whitney went to Connecticut.</field>
    <field name="text">There he had a shop for making the gins.</field>
    <field name="text">When the suits began he had to return to Georgia.</field>
    <field name="text">In this way two years went by.</field>
    <field name="text">By this time everyone knew the value of the gin.</field>
    <field name="text">Mr. Whitney went to New York.</field>
    <field name="text">There he became ill.</field>
    <field name="text">His illness lasted three weeks.</field>
    <field name="text">Then he was able to go on to New Haven.</field>
    <field name="text">[Illustration: SAW-GIN, 1794.]</field>
    <field name="text">There he found that his shop had been destroyed by fire.</field>
    <field name="text">All his machines and papers were burned.</field>
    <field name="text">He was four thousand dollars in debt.</field>
    <field name="text">But neither Mr. Miller nor Mr. Whitney were the kind of men who give up easily.</field>
    <field name="text">Mr. Miller wrote that he would give all his time, thought, labor, and all the money he could borrow to help.</field>
    <field name="text">"It shall never be said that we gave up when a little perseverance would have carried us through," he said.</field>
    <field name="text">About this time bad news came from England.</field>
    <field name="text">The cotton, you remember, was then all sent there for manufacture.</field>
    <field name="text">English manufacturers now claimed that the cotton was injured by the gin.</field>
    <field name="text">This was in 1796.</field>
    <field name="text">Miller and Whitney had thirty gins working in different places in Georgia.</field>
    <field name="text">Some were worked by cattle and horses.</field>
    <field name="text">Others were run by water.</field>
    <field name="text">Soon, however, the manufacturers found that the Whitney cotton gin did not injure the cotton.</field>
    <field name="text">The first lawsuit was decided against Miller and Whitney.</field>
    <field name="text">They asked for another trial.</field>
    <field name="text">But this was refused them.</field>
    <field name="text">Everywhere through the South they were cheated and robbed.</field>
    <field name="text">Yet all the time the South was growing richer because of the cotton gin.</field>
    <field name="text">Slaves grew more and more valuable.</field>
    <field name="text">For negroes can endure the heat of the cotton fields.</field>
    <field name="text">But white men can not.</field>
    <field name="text">The planters of the South bought more and more slaves.</field>
    <field name="text">So slavery grew stronger because of the cotton gin.</field>
    <field name="text">Several states made contracts with Mr. Whitney.</field>
    <field name="text">They agreed to pay him certain sums of money.</field>
    <field name="text">But South Carolina broke her contract.</field>
    <field name="text">All these things made Mr. Whitney sick at heart.</field>
    <field name="text">He said that he had tried hard to do right by every one.</field>
    <field name="text">And it stung him to the very soul to be treated like a swindler or a villain.</field>
    <field name="text">The people of Georgia tried to prove that somebody in Switzerland had invented the cotton gin.</field>
    <field name="text">Tennessee broke its contract.</field>
    <field name="text">There were high-minded men who tried to help Mr. Whitney.</field>
    <field name="text">They were able to do only a little for him.</field>
    <field name="text">In 1803, Mr. Miller died.</field>
    <field name="text">Mr. Whitney was then left to fight his battles alone.</field>
    <field name="text">Things grew a little brighter as time went on.</field>
    <field name="text">Mr. Whitney received some money on his invention.</field>
    <field name="text">But the greater part of it had to be spent in lawsuits.</field>
    <field name="text">A suit was begun in the United States Court.</field>
    <field name="text">But the time of his patent was almost out.</field>
    <field name="text">He had made six journeys to Georgia.</field>
    <field name="text">One gentleman said that he never knew another man so persevering.</field>
    <field name="text">In 1798, Mr. Whitney made a contract with the government of the United States.</field>
    <field name="text">By this contract he was to manufacture fire-arms.</field>
    <field name="text">He established his factory near New Haven.</field>
    <field name="text">The place is now called Whitneyville.</field>
    <field name="text">It is a beautiful place.</field>
    <field name="text">A waterfall furnished the power to run his machinery.</field>
    <field name="text">Here Mr. Whitney worked hard.</field>
    <field name="text">He had machinery to make.</field>
    <field name="text">He had to teach his own workmen.</field>
    <field name="text">For eight years he worked to fill this contract.</field>
    <field name="text">He arose as soon as day appeared.</field>
    <field name="text">Look in any part of the factory you might, you would see something which he, himself had done.</field>
    <field name="text">He improved many tools.</field>
    <field name="text">He made better guns than had ever been made.</field>
    <field name="text">So that for these things, too, our country is indebted to Mr. Whitney.</field>
    <field name="text">In 1812, he made new contracts.</field>
    <field name="text">Another war with England began in that year.</field>
    <field name="text">Mr. Whitney's guns never failed to be all right.</field>
    <field name="text">Other men took contracts of the same kind.</field>
    <field name="text">But their guns were failures.</field>
    <field name="text">Mr. Calhoun, the Secretary of War, said to Mr. Whitney, "You are saving your country seventy-five thousand dollars a year."</field>
    <field name="text">This was by his improvements in fire-arms.</field>
    <field name="text">Mr. Whitney tried to get the government to extend the time of the patent upon the cotton-gin.</field>
    <field name="text">But this was refused.</field>
    <field name="text">That did not seem very grateful, did it?</field>
    <field name="text">Robert Fulton, the inventor of the first steamboat, was his friend.</field>
    <field name="text">They had many troubles in common.</field>
    <field name="text">Mr. Whitney's last days were his happiest days.</field>
    <field name="text">Such patience, perseverance, and skill must count in the long run.</field>
    <field name="text">His factory made him quite a rich man.</field>
    <field name="text">Some of the southern states showed their gratitude.</field>
    <field name="text">In 1817, Mr. Whitney married Miss Edwards of Connecticut.</field>
    <field name="text">He had a son and three daughters.</field>
    <field name="text">The people of New Haven respected him.</field>
    <field name="text">They gave him great honor.</field>
    <field name="text">He died on January 8, 1825.</field>
    <field name="text">The little cotton-gin had done a great work.</field>
    <field name="text">The sunny South was covered with beautiful plantations.</field>
    <field name="text">The cotton fields shone in the sunlight.</field>
    <field name="text">[Illustration]</field>
    <field name="text">Riches were beginning to fill the pockets of the planters.</field>
    <field name="text">Only one blight remained upon the land.</field>
    <field name="text">This was the dreadful system of slavery.</field>
    <field name="text">And that, too, has been destroyed.</field>
    <field name="text">We wish that Mr. Whitney might see the South of to-day.</field>
    <field name="text">He did not live to know how great a curse slavery might be.</field>
    <field name="text">He did not foresee that his cotton-gin might help to cause a great war.</field>
    <field name="text">Yet the blue and the gray fought and died.</field>
    <field name="text">The blood of many a hero stained a southern field.</field>
    <field name="text">All this that the cotton-pickers might be free!</field>
    <field name="text">All this that our country might be truly "the land of the free and the home of the brave!"</field>
    <field name="text">[Illustration: S.F.B. MORSE.]</field>
  </doc>
</add>
