<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
  <doc>
    <field name="number">3</field>
    <field name="text" />
    <field name="text">SAMUEL FINLEY BREESE MORSE.</field>
    <field name="text">If everything were now as it was in 1791, what a queer place this world of ours would be to us!</field>
    <field name="text">A hundred years ago!</field>
    <field name="text">Suppose we imagine ourselves living in the year 1800.</field>
    <field name="text">The railroads then were very few and poor.</field>
    <field name="text">"Fulton's Folly," the first steamboat, had not yet frightened the sailors in New York Harbor, with its long line of black smoke.</field>
    <field name="text">Lighting by means of gas was yet unknown.</field>
    <field name="text">Electric lights were not even dreamed of.</field>
    <field name="text">Even kerosene, which we think makes so poor a light, was then unused.</field>
    <field name="text">So there are many, many things, common and useful to us now, which were unknown to the world in 1800.</field>
    <field name="text">You have heard of the giant, Steam.</field>
    <field name="text">There is yet another giant which God has placed in the world for man's use.</field>
    <field name="text">This is Electricity.</field>
    <field name="text">Is it not strange that this great power should have been so long unused in the world?</field>
    <field name="text">Boys and girls can understand how useful this power now is.</field>
    <field name="text">So you will be interested in knowing something of the man who helped to introduce to the world this great giant, electricity.</field>
    <field name="text">The baby who was given this long name, Samuel Finley Breese Morse, was born in Charlestown, Massachusetts.</field>
    <field name="text">The date of his birth was April 27, 1791.</field>
    <field name="text">He was called Samuel Finley for his great-grandfather.</field>
    <field name="text">His mother's name, as a girl, was Elizabeth Breese.</field>
    <field name="text">You will see that he won fame enough to cover each and every one of these names.</field>
    <field name="text">Finley Morse had, as he grew older, two brothers younger than himself.</field>
    <field name="text">Their names were Sidney E. Morse, and Richard Cary Morse.</field>
    <field name="text">Finley was sent first to an old lady's school.</field>
    <field name="text">He was but four years old when he started.</field>
    <field name="text">The school was very near his home.</field>
    <field name="text">The school mistress was known as, "Old Ma'am Rand."</field>
    <field name="text">She was an invalid and unable to leave her chair.</field>
    <field name="text">So she had a long rattan.</field>
    <field name="text">When the children did not mind, she could, with her long rattan, reach them at the further side of the room.</field>
    <field name="text">One punishment of Mrs. Rand's was to pin a naughty child to her dress.</field>
    <field name="text">As early as this part of his life, Finley Morse tried his hand at drawing.</field>
    <field name="text">He drew Mrs. Rand's picture upon a chest of drawers.</field>
    <field name="text">Instead of a pencil he used a pin.</field>
    <field name="text">So Mrs. Rand pinned him to her dress.</field>
    <field name="text">Of course he did not like that.</field>
    <field name="text">He tried to get away.</field>
    <field name="text">This tore the dress.</field>
    <field name="text">Then Mrs. Rand had to use her rattan.</field>
    <field name="text">When seven years of age Finley was sent to school at Andover.</field>
    <field name="text">He went to Phillip's Academy.</field>
    <field name="text">While there the father wrote letters to his boy.</field>
    <field name="text">He gave his boy good advice.</field>
    <field name="text">He told him about George Washington.</field>
    <field name="text">He also told him about another great man.</field>
    <field name="text">This man was a statesman of Holland.</field>
    <field name="text">He did all the business for that republic.</field>
    <field name="text">Yet he had time to go to evening amusements.</field>
    <field name="text">Some one asked this statesman how he did this.</field>
    <field name="text">He said there was nothing so easy, for that it was only doing one thing at a time, and never putting off anything until to-morrow that could be done to-day.</field>
    <field name="text">Finley's parents were always kind to him.</field>
    <field name="text">He soon became a manly boy.</field>
    <field name="text">He was the kind of boy who seemed to know that he must one day be a man.</field>
    <field name="text">So he worked hard at school.</field>
    <field name="text">He began early to think and act for himself.</field>
    <field name="text">When he was but thirteen he wrote a sketch of the "Life of Demosthenes."</field>
    <field name="text">He sent it to his father.</field>
    <field name="text">This his father kept carefully.</field>
    <field name="text">It showed the genius, learning and taste of his boy.</field>
    <field name="text">This bright boy was ready for college at the age of fourteen.</field>
    <field name="text">But his father thought it best to keep him at home for a year.</field>
    <field name="text">Finley, when a boy, was always fond of drawing.</field>
    <field name="text">When but fifteen, he painted a fairly good picture in water colors.</field>
    <field name="text">This represented a room in his father's house.</field>
    <field name="text">His father, his two brothers and himself stood by a table.</field>
    <field name="text">His mother sat in a chair.</field>
    <field name="text">On the table was a globe, at which they were all looking.</field>
    <field name="text">His room at college was covered with pictures of his own making.</field>
    <field name="text">One of these was called, "Freshmen Climbing the Hill of Science."</field>
    <field name="text">The poor fellows were scrambling to the top of a hill on their hands and knees.</field>
    <field name="text">Finley had taken no lessons in art, yet he drew many portraits.</field>
    <field name="text">The other boys were all delighted to have their pictures drawn by him.</field>
    <field name="text">They paid him a dollar apiece.</field>
    <field name="text">This kept him in spending money.</field>
    <field name="text">He also painted upon ivory.</field>
    <field name="text">For these he had five dollars each.</field>
    <field name="text">So, when Finley Morse graduated from Yale college, he was more fond of drawing and painting than of anything else.</field>
    <field name="text">Finley at this time was a fine looking boy.</field>
    <field name="text">He had a pleasant smile.</field>
    <field name="text">He was always courteous.</field>
    <field name="text">Every one liked him.</field>
    <field name="text">He was as fond of a frolic as any one.</field>
    <field name="text">At one time the college cooks did not do their work to suit the boys.</field>
    <field name="text">So the boys gave them a mock trial.</field>
    <field name="text">They sent a report of the trial to the college president.</field>
    <field name="text">The bad cooks were dismissed.</field>
    <field name="text">Afterwards the boys had better things to eat.</field>
    <field name="text">At another time the boys went to a paper mill near by.</field>
    <field name="text">They bought a great quantity of paper.</field>
    <field name="text">This they made into a baloon.</field>
    <field name="text">It was eighteen feet in length.</field>
    <field name="text">They filled it with air, and sent it on its journey.</field>
    <field name="text">It sailed finely, and soon was out of sight.</field>
    <field name="text">They tried it again.</field>
    <field name="text">The second time it took fire and was soon nothing but ashes.</field>
    <field name="text">About this time Finley heard his first lecture upon electricity.</field>
    <field name="text">After graduating, he returned to his father's house in Charlestown.</field>
    <field name="text">There he wrote a letter to his brothers with a queer kind of ink.</field>
    <field name="text">The writing did not show at all until heated by fire.</field>
    <field name="text">His brothers had to write to him to find out how to read it.</field>
    <field name="text">About this time Finley made a new friend.</field>
    <field name="text">This friend was Washington Allston.</field>
    <field name="text">Mr. Allston was a great painter.</field>
    <field name="text">He learned to love Finley Morse.</field>
    <field name="text">Mr. Allston spent most of his time in London.</field>
    <field name="text">Finley begged his people to allow him to go to London with Mr. Allston.</field>
    <field name="text">They finally gave their consent.</field>
    <field name="text">So Mr. Morse made his first voyage across the Atlantic.</field>
    <field name="text">They landed at Liverpool.</field>
    <field name="text">They had to go from there to London in a stage coach.</field>
    <field name="text">As soon as he arrived he wrote to his parents.</field>
    <field name="text">In his letter he said that he wished they could hear from each other in an instant.</field>
    <field name="text">"But three thousand miles are not passed over in an instant.</field>
    <field name="text">So we must wait four long weeks before we can hear from each other again."</field>
    <field name="text">Even then he longed for a telegraph.</field>
    <field name="text">In London he had the help of another great artist.</field>
    <field name="text">This was Benjamin West.</field>
    <field name="text">He, too, was an American.</field>
    <field name="text">Mr. Morse wished to become a student in the Royal Academy.</field>
    <field name="text">He had to make a drawing of Hercules.</field>
    <field name="text">Hercules, you know, was one of the heroes of early Greece.</field>
    <field name="text">The story is that he did very many brave deeds.</field>
    <field name="text">Finley's drawing was to be taken to Mr. West.</field>
    <field name="text">He worked very hard upon it for two weeks.</field>
    <field name="text">Then he went to Mr. West with it.</field>
    <field name="text">Mr. West said, "Very well, sir, very well; go on and finish it."</field>
    <field name="text">"It is finished," replied Finley.</field>
    <field name="text">"Oh, no," said Mr. West. "Look here, and here, and here."</field>
    <field name="text">So, when the mistakes were pointed out, Finley saw them.</field>
    <field name="text">He took the drawing home and worked patiently for another week.</field>
    <field name="text">Then he brought it to Mr. West again.</field>
    <field name="text">Mr. West handed it back to Mr. Morse, saying:</field>
    <field name="text">"Very well indeed, sir. Go on and finish it."</field>
    <field name="text">"Is it not finished?" said Mr. Morse, for he was almost discouraged.</field>
    <field name="text">"See," said Mr. West, "you have not marked this muscle nor that finger joint."</field>
    <field name="text">So another three days were spent on the drawing.</field>
    <field name="text">Again it was taken back.</field>
    <field name="text">"Very clever indeed," said Mr. West, "very clever. Now go on and finish it."</field>
    <field name="text">"I cannot finish it," replied Mr. Morse.</field>
    <field name="text">Then the old man patted him on the shoulder and said:</field>
    <field name="text">"Well, I have tried you long enough.</field>
    <field name="text">"Now, sir, you have learned more by this drawing than you would have learned in double the time by a dozen half finished drawings.</field>
    <field name="text">"Finish one picture, sir, and you are a painter."</field>
    <field name="text">Mr. Morse took this good advice.</field>
    <field name="text">He went to work upon a large picture.</field>
    <field name="text">It was a picture of the "Dying Hercules."</field>
    <field name="text">He first modeled his picture in clay.</field>
    <field name="text">This he did so well that he received a gold medal for it. This was on May 13, 1813.</field>
    <field name="text">His picture, too, was given great praise.</field>
    <field name="text">It was counted as one of the twelve best among the two thousand pictures.</field>
    <field name="text">So Mr. Morse went on patiently and carefully in this work.</field>
    <field name="text">He made many good friends in London.</field>
    <field name="text">One of these friends was the poet, Coleridge.</field>
    <field name="text">Mr. Morse was a great comfort to his parents.</field>
    <field name="text">He was careful with his money.</field>
    <field name="text">He and a young Mr. Leslie, lived and painted together.</field>
    <field name="text">He spent all his money to get helps in his work.</field>
    <field name="text">He visited all the picture galleries, and spent days in the study of pictures.</field>
    <field name="text">At this time England and America were at war.</field>
    <field name="text">Americans were sometimes made prisoners and kept in the prisons of England.</field>
    <field name="text">Mr. Morse tried to help some of them.</field>
    <field name="text">You have heard of the great French general, Napoleon.</field>
    <field name="text">You know of the many wars he had.</field>
    <field name="text">In 1815, Napoleon met his enemies, the English and Prussians.</field>
    <field name="text">They had a battle at Waterloo.</field>
    <field name="text">Napoleon was defeated.</field>
    <field name="text">The people of England were anxious for news.</field>
    <field name="text">But how slowly news came in those days!</field>
    <field name="text">It took many days to carry the good tidings.</field>
    <field name="text">The battle was fought on the 18th day of June.</field>
    <field name="text">It was not until July that the news came of the victory of the English general.</field>
    <field name="text">Mr. Morse wrote about it to his parents.</field>
    <field name="text">He told how anxiously the people had waited.</field>
    <field name="text">Finally the people heard the booming of cannon.</field>
    <field name="text">The bells were rung.</field>
    <field name="text">People laughed and cried for joy.</field>
    <field name="text">Would it not seem strange to us now to wait for our news so long?</field>
    <field name="text">Yet the inventor of the telegraph had to wait often very long.</field>
    <field name="text">But at last the time came for Mr. Morse to return to America.</field>
    <field name="text">He sailed in August, 1815.</field>
    <field name="text">He bore with him the good wishes of his many friends in London.</field>
    <field name="text">He had a stormy voyage.</field>
    <field name="text">A ship signaled his ship for help.</field>
    <field name="text">The captain did not wish to send help.</field>
    <field name="text">He said he had all he could do to attend to his own ship.</field>
    <field name="text">Mr. Morse told him that, if he did not help them, he would publish the facts when they reached America.</field>
    <field name="text">So the captain thought better of it.</field>
    <field name="text">He helped to save the ship.</field>
    <field name="text">When he landed on his return Mr. Morse found that the people of America had heard of him.</field>
    <field name="text">They knew of the fine pictures he had painted.</field>
    <field name="text">He was now but twenty-four years of age.</field>
    <field name="text">He set up a studio in Boston.</field>
    <field name="text">But the people of America were not as interested in art then as now.</field>
    <field name="text">He waited many months for something to do.</field>
    <field name="text">But nobody came for a picture.</field>
    <field name="text">He left Boston almost penniless.</field>
    <field name="text">Then he began painting portraits in different places.</field>
    <field name="text">He received fifteen dollars for each portrait.</field>
    <field name="text">He went to Concord, New Hampshire.</field>
    <field name="text">There he met a beautiful young lady.</field>
    <field name="text">Her name was Lucretia P. Walker.</field>
    <field name="text">She had a very sweet temper.</field>
    <field name="text">She always used good sense.</field>
    <field name="text">Mr. Morse became more and more successful with his portraits.</field>
    <field name="text">He received more money for them.</field>
    <field name="text">He went on a journey to the South.</field>
    <field name="text">There he found much to do.</field>
    <field name="text">He made three thousand dollars.</field>
    <field name="text">Then he came back to Concord.</field>
    <field name="text">There he married Miss Walker.</field>
    <field name="text">Mr. and Mrs. Morse lived for a few years in South Carolina.</field>
    <field name="text">Then they came to New Haven, Connecticut.</field>
    <field name="text">His father came to live with them there.</field>
    <field name="text">Mr. Morse began to paint a great picture at Washington.</field>
    <field name="text">It was called "The House of Representatives."</field>
    <field name="text">Washington is the capital city of the United States.</field>
    <field name="text">The picture, when finished, was very beautiful.</field>
    <field name="text">It was sold at last to an Englishman.</field>
    <field name="text">About this time a great friend of America visited Washington.</field>
    <field name="text">Have you heard of General La Fayette?</field>
    <field name="text">You can read what great things he did for our country.</field>
    <field name="text">Every American loved him then.</field>
    <field name="text">Even the people who live now, love his memory.</field>
    <field name="text">Mr. Morse was engaged to paint the portrait of General La Fayette.</field>
    <field name="text">He began the picture.</field>
    <field name="text">Before he had finished, he received dreadful news from home.</field>
    <field name="text">His loved wife had died very suddenly.</field>
    <field name="text">He hastened home.</field>
    <field name="text">It seemed too hard to bear.</field>
    <field name="text">Not long afterwards he lost his father.</field>
    <field name="text">He then went to live in New York.</field>
    <field name="text">There he worked hard at his art.</field>
    <field name="text">His artist friends made him president of their society.</field>
    <field name="text">This was the National Academy.</field>
    <field name="text">While in New York he heard some lectures about electricity.</field>
    <field name="text">He thought about it and talked much with his friends.</field>
    <field name="text">He wished to visit beautiful Italy.</field>
    <field name="text">So, in 1829, he sailed for Europe.</field>
    <field name="text">His friends there gave him a hearty welcome.</field>
    <field name="text">He visited many cities.</field>
    <field name="text">He met General La Fayette again.</field>
    <field name="text">He visited him in his home.</field>
    <field name="text">Mr. Morse had always been fond of inventions.</field>
    <field name="text">He himself invented a pump at one time.</field>
    <field name="text">At another, he tried his hand at making a machine for cutting marble.</field>
    <field name="text">He was always experimenting with colors, and other things used by artists.</field>
    <field name="text">The year 1832 had arrived.</field>
    <field name="text">You will see, by and by, that it is a good date to remember.</field>
    <field name="text">People knew almost nothing about speed in traveling.</field>
    <field name="text">In that year the longest railroad was in the southern part of the United States.</field>
    <field name="text">It was one hundred thirty-five miles long.</field>
    <field name="text">The next longer was in England.</field>
    <field name="text">It was thirty miles long.</field>
    <field name="text">The next was in Massachusetts.</field>
    <field name="text">It was ten miles long.</field>
    <field name="text">The mails were carried in coaches.</field>
    <field name="text">On the first day of October, 1832, Mr. Morse sailed for America.</field>
    <field name="text">The name of this ship was the "Sully."</field>
    <field name="text">The passengers were much interested in some things which had lately been found out about electricity.</field>
    <field name="text">People had long known that lightning and electricity were the same.</field>
    <field name="text">Signals had been made with electricity.</field>
    <field name="text">But the thought which came to Mr. Morse had never entered the mind of man before.</field>
    <field name="text">He could think of nothing but a telegraph.</field>
    <field name="text">He thought night and day.</field>
    <field name="text">He seemed to see the end from the beginning.</field>
    <field name="text">As he sat upon the deck of the ship after dinner, he drew out a little note book.</field>
    <field name="text">He began his plan in this little book.</field>
    <field name="text">From the beginning he said, "If a message will go ten miles without dropping, I can make it go around the globe."</field>
    <field name="text">And he said this again and again during the years that came after.</field>
    <field name="text">Sleep forsook him.</field>
    <field name="text">But one morning at the breakfast table he announced his plan.</field>
    <field name="text">He showed it to the passengers.</field>
    <field name="text">And five years after, when the model was built, it was found to be like the one shown that morning on board the ship "Sully."</field>
    <field name="text">"The steed called Lightning (say the Fates)     Was tamed in the United States;     'Twas Franklin's hand that caught the horse,     'Twas harnessed by Professor Morse."</field>
    <field name="text">Upon landing in America a long struggle began.</field>
    <field name="text">For twelve long years, Mr. Morse worked to get people to notice his invention.</field>
    <field name="text">[Illustration: DIAGRAM SHOWING THE MORSE ALPHABET AND   ARRANGEMENT OF THE TELEGRAPH LINE.]</field>
    <field name="text">It would take much money to construct a real telegraph.</field>
    <field name="text">But money Mr. Morse did not have.</field>
    <field name="text">He had three motherless children to provide for.</field>
    <field name="text">He lived in a room in a fifth story of a building belonging to his brothers.</field>
    <field name="text">This room was his study, studio, bed chamber, parlor, kitchen, drawing room and work shop.</field>
    <field name="text">On one side of the room was his cot bed.</field>
    <field name="text">On the other were his tools.</field>
    <field name="text">He brought his simple food to his room at night.</field>
    <field name="text">This he did, that no one might see how little he had to eat.</field>
    <field name="text">He often gave lessons in painting.</field>
    <field name="text">One pupil did not pay promptly.</field>
    <field name="text">Mr. Morse asked to be paid.</field>
    <field name="text">The pupil gave him ten dollars, asking if he would accept it.</field>
    <field name="text">He said it would keep him from starving.</field>
    <field name="text">He had had nothing to eat for twenty-four hours.</field>
    <field name="text">The government, at this time, was giving some work to American artists.</field>
    <field name="text">Mr. Morse knew he deserved to have a picture to paint.</field>
    <field name="text">But, through a mistake, he was not given one.</field>
    <field name="text">He felt much hurt by this.</field>
    <field name="text">But perhaps he would not have pushed his telegraph through, if he had been given plenty of painting to do.</field>
    <field name="text">As it was, Morse, the painter, became Morse, the inventor.</field>
    <field name="text">It was not until 1837 that Mr. Morse had his wonderful invention ready to exhibit.</field>
    <field name="text">During that year many people saw it.</field>
    <field name="text">Many thought it a silly toy.</field>
    <field name="text">Few dreamed of its importance.</field>
    <field name="text">Mr. Alfred Vail, whose father and brother had large brass and iron works, was one of those who believed in it.</field>
    <field name="text">Mr. Vail decided to assist Mr. Morse.</field>
    <field name="text">He was young and liked machinery.</field>
    <field name="text">Long after, Mr. Morse said that much of the success of the telegraph was due to Mr. Vail.</field>
    <field name="text">In 1838, Mr. Morse asked Congress to give him aid.</field>
    <field name="text">He wished to build a telegraph between Baltimore and Washington.</field>
    <field name="text">The President and others saw the telegraph exhibited.</field>
    <field name="text">A gentleman, named Mr. F.O.J. Smith, helped Mr. Morse with money.</field>
    <field name="text">But many Congressmen laughed at the idea.</field>
    <field name="text">Do you not think they felt ashamed when they found how great a thing they had been laughing at?</field>
    <field name="text">While waiting for Congress to decide, Mr. Morse went to Europe again.</field>
    <field name="text">He tried to get a patent in London, but it was refused him.</field>
    <field name="text">The French people gave him a paper which didn't mean much.</field>
    <field name="text">He met some great men, however, who did all they could for him.</field>
    <field name="text">Did you ever see a daguerreotype?</field>
    <field name="text">It is an old fashioned portrait.</field>
    <field name="text">Perhaps you can find some at home.</field>
    <field name="text">Mr. Morse met in Paris the man who first took these pictures.</field>
    <field name="text">His name was Mr. Daguerre.</field>
    <field name="text">You see how the pictures were named.</field>
    <field name="text">He was exhibiting his pictures at this time.</field>
    <field name="text">So the two greatest things in Paris in those days were the electro-magnetic telegraph and daguerreotypes.</field>
    <field name="text">Mr. Daguerre and Mr. Morse became fast friends.</field>
    <field name="text">Mr. Daguerre taught Mr. Morse how to take daguerreotypes.</field>
    <field name="text">When Mr. Morse returned to America, he took some portraits of this kind.</field>
    <field name="text">He also taught others how to do so.</field>
    <field name="text">Having returned to America, he found plenty to do.</field>
    <field name="text">He wished to try the telegraph under water.</field>
    <field name="text">He arranged about two miles of wire.</field>
    <field name="text">He put it into New York Harbor.</field>
    <field name="text">A row boat was used in placing it.</field>
    <field name="text">It was a beautiful moonlight night.</field>
    <field name="text">People walking along the shore might well wonder what kind of fish were to be caught with such a long line.</field>
    <field name="text">At day break Professor Morse was ready for his experiment.</field>
    <field name="text">Two or three characters were sent on the line.</field>
    <field name="text">Then no more could be sent.</field>
    <field name="text">Some sailors, in pulling up their anchor, had caught the wire.</field>
    <field name="text">They pulled in about two hundred feet.</field>
    <field name="text">Then they cut the wire.</field>
    <field name="text">So ended the first cable.</field>
    <field name="text">The Vails had been good friends to Mr. Morse.</field>
    <field name="text">But they became afraid to spend any more money.</field>
    <field name="text">Then, indeed, Mr. Morse was in despair.</field>
    <field name="text">A bill had been brought before Congress, asking for thirty thousand dollars.</field>
    <field name="text">This was to build the trial telegraph line.</field>
    <field name="text">Oh, how anxiously Mr. Morse waited!</field>
    <field name="text">Delay after delay came.</field>
    <field name="text">Many Congressmen in their speeches, made all manner of fun of the bill.</field>
    <field name="text">Twilight came upon the evening of March 3rd, 1842.</field>
    <field name="text">It was the last day of the session of Congress.</field>
    <field name="text">There were still one hundred and nineteen bills to dispose of.</field>
    <field name="text">It seemed impossible that the telegraph bill could be reached.</field>
    <field name="text">Mr. Morse had patiently waited all day.</field>
    <field name="text">At last he gave up all hope.</field>
    <field name="text">He left the building and went to his hotel.</field>
    <field name="text">He planned to leave for New York on an early train.</field>
    <field name="text">As he came down to breakfast next morning, a young lady met him.</field>
    <field name="text">"I have come to congratulate you," she exclaimed.</field>
    <field name="text">"Upon what?" inquired the professor.</field>
    <field name="text">"Upon the passage of your bill," she replied.</field>
    <field name="text">"Impossible! Its fate was sealed last evening.</field>
    <field name="text">You must be mistaken."</field>
    <field name="text">"Not at all," said the young lady; "father sent me to tell you that your bill was passed. It was passed just five minutes before the close of the session."</field>
    <field name="text">Mr. Morse was almost overcome with the news.</field>
    <field name="text">He promised the young lady that she should send the first message over the new line.</field>
    <field name="text">Mr. Morse received a sad message in the midst of his joy.</field>
    <field name="text">This was the news of the death of his dearest friend, Mr. Allston.</field>
    <field name="text">He hastened to the home of his friend in Cambridge.</field>
    <field name="text">The brush with which Mr. Allston had been painting was still moist.</field>
    <field name="text">Mr. Morse begged this as a memorial of his friend.</field>
    <field name="text">He afterwards gave it to the National Academy.</field>
    <field name="text">Now that the bill was passed, how hard he and his friend worked to build the line!</field>
    <field name="text">They tried putting the wires underground.</field>
    <field name="text">But this proved very expensive.</field>
    <field name="text">Then they tried the poles as we have them now.</field>
    <field name="text">This succeeded nicely.</field>
    <field name="text">1844 was the year for the appointing of a new President.</field>
    <field name="text">The Whig party were to hold their convention at Baltimore, in May.</field>
    <field name="text">The managers of the telegraph worked hard to get the line done before the meeting.</field>
    <field name="text">And, although the line was not finished, signals were arranged by which the message could be given.</field>
    <field name="text">At last the day came.</field>
    <field name="text">Henry Clay was nominated for President.</field>
    <field name="text">The news was sent by the wires to Washington.</field>
    <field name="text">Passengers arrived from Baltimore an hour later.</field>
    <field name="text">They were astonished to find the news already known.</field>
    <field name="text">On the 24th of May the line was ready for its test.</field>
    <field name="text">Every one was anxious.</field>
    <field name="text">Mr. Vail was at the Baltimore end of the line.</field>
    <field name="text">Miss Ellsworth, the young lady who had the promise of sending the first message, was with Mr. Morse.</field>
    <field name="text">Remember the twelve long, weary, anxious years, during which Mr. Morse had worked and waited.</field>
    <field name="text">It was an anxious moment.</field>
    <field name="text">Miss Ellsworth chose her message from the Bible.</field>
    <field name="text">It is found in Numbers, 23rd chapter, 23rd verse.</field>
    <field name="text">The words are: "What hath God wrought!"</field>
    <field name="text">This was received at once by Mr. Vail.</field>
    <field name="text">Professor Morse said this of the words of the message:--</field>
    <field name="text">"It baptized the American Telegraph with the name of the author."</field>
    <field name="text">He meant by this, that God was the author of the telegraph.</field>
    <field name="text">What a glad, happy time followed!</field>
    <field name="text">Everybody congratulated Mr. Morse.</field>
    <field name="text">The democratic convention took place two days later.</field>
    <field name="text">There was much excitement.</field>
    <field name="text">James K. Polk was nominated for President.</field>
    <field name="text">All sorts of messages were sent over the new telegraph line.</field>
    <field name="text">Mr. Morse loved his country.</field>
    <field name="text">And through his whole life worked for its interests.</field>
    <field name="text">He rejoiced in having his invention called an American invention.</field>
    <field name="text">He was at one time in Europe.</field>
    <field name="text">His friend, Mr. F.O.J. Smith, was embarking on his voyage for home.</field>
    <field name="text">Mr. Morse said to him:--</field>
    <field name="text">"When you arrive in sight of dear America, bless it for me.</field>
    <field name="text">"And when you land, kiss the very ground for me.</field>
    <field name="text">"Land of lands! Oh, that all our country-men would but know their blessings!</field>
    <field name="text">"God hath not dealt so with any nation.</field>
    <field name="text">"We ought to be the best, as well as the happiest and most prosperous of all nations.</field>
    <field name="text">"Nor should we forget to whom we are in debt for all these blessings.</field>
    <field name="text">"'Righteousness exalteth a nation, but sin is a reproach to any nation.'"</field>
    <field name="text">*       *       *       *       *</field>
    <field name="text">There were still many hard things for Mr. Morse to endure.</field>
    <field name="text">Wicked men tried to steal his invention from him.</field>
    <field name="text">They pretended to have invented telegraphs.</field>
    <field name="text">The nations of Europe did not treat him justly.</field>
    <field name="text">But, little by little, the telegraph lines were built over the country.</field>
    <field name="text">Little, by little, the world came to know and love the name of Samuel F.B. Morse.</field>
    <field name="text">Honors of all sorts were given him.</field>
    <field name="text">But, through all, he was the same kind, patient man.</field>
    <field name="text">The Sultan of Turkey was the first foreign prince to honor Mr. Morse.</field>
    <field name="text">But he was followed by many others.</field>
    <field name="text">You have noticed that Mr. Morse never had a chance to enjoy a home.</field>
    <field name="text">In 1847, he bought a beautiful home upon the Hudson.</field>
    <field name="text">In the following year he married Miss Griswold, a lady born at Sault Ste. Marie.</field>
    <field name="text">They called their new home Locust Grove.</field>
    <field name="text">There they enjoyed life greatly.</field>
    <field name="text">Professor Morse had a telegraph instrument in his study.</field>
    <field name="text">He afterwards bought a beautiful home in New York City.</field>
    <field name="text">There they spent their winters.</field>
    <field name="text">These words were written by a friend to Mrs. Morse, alluding to her husband:--</field>
    <field name="text">"Though he did not 'snatch the thunder from the heaven,' he gave the electric current thought, and bound the earth in light."</field>
    <field name="text">To Mr. Morse belongs also the honor of the submarine telegraph.</field>
    <field name="text">A successful telegraph of this kind was laid near New York City.</field>
    <field name="text">Other gentlemen became interested in this.</field>
    <field name="text">Chief among these were Mr. Cyrus W. Field and his brother David Dudley Field.</field>
    <field name="text">The story of the cable laid across the Atlantic is a long one.</field>
    <field name="text">But Mr. Morse lived to see this, too, a success.</field>
    <field name="text">When Mr. Morse was eighty years of age, his statue was erected in Central Park, New York.</field>
    <field name="text">This was done by the telegraph operators of the country.</field>
    <field name="text">It represented Mr. Morse as sending the first message of the telegraph, "What hath God wrought."</field>
    <field name="text">Mr. Morse was present when the statue was unveiled.</field>
    <field name="text">In 1872 he became very ill.</field>
    <field name="text">His busy life was at an end.</field>
    <field name="text">The whole country mourned, as news flashed over the wires that Professor Morse was dying.</field>
    <field name="text">The light was going out of those bright, kind eyes.</field>
    <field name="text">The fingers that harnessed the steed, Lightning were powerless.</field>
    <field name="text">The great brain, that had worked so hard for the world, was ready for rest.</field>
    <field name="text">The great heart, that never kept an unkind thought, ceased to beat.</field>
    <field name="text">All America mourned for him.</field>
    <field name="text">Messages were received from Europe, Asia and Africa, paying tribute to the dead.</field>
    <field name="text">Few men have lived such lives as did Samuel Finley Breese Morse.</field>
    <field name="text">[Illustration]</field>
    <field name="text">[Illustration: PETER COOPER.]</field>
  </doc>
</add>
