<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
  <doc>
    <field name="number">4</field>
    <field name="text" />
    <field name="text">PETER COOPER.</field>
    <field name="text">On the seventh of April, in 1883, the great city of New York was in mourning. Flags were at half-mast. The bells tolled.</field>
    <field name="text">Shops were closed, but in the windows were pictures of a kind-faced, white-haired man.</field>
    <field name="text">These pictures were draped in black.</field>
    <field name="text">All day long tens of thousands of people passed by an open coffin in one of the churches.</field>
    <field name="text">Some of these people were governors, some millionaires.</field>
    <field name="text">There were poor women, too, with little children in their arms.</field>
    <field name="text">There were workmen in their common clothes.</field>
    <field name="text">There were ragged newsboys.</field>
    <field name="text">And all these people had aching hearts.</field>
    <field name="text">The great daily papers printed many columns about the sad event.</field>
    <field name="text">People in England sent messages by the Atlantic cable that they, too, had sad hearts.</field>
    <field name="text">Who was this man for whom the world mourned on that April day?</field>
    <field name="text">Was he a president? Oh, no.</field>
    <field name="text">A great general? Far from it.</field>
    <field name="text">Did he live magnificently and have splendid carriages and fine diamonds?</field>
    <field name="text">No, he was simply Peter Cooper, a man ninety-two years old, and the best loved man in America.</field>
    <field name="text">Had he given money?</field>
    <field name="text">Yes, but other men in our country do that</field>
    <field name="text">Had he traveled abroad, and so become widely known?</field>
    <field name="text">No, he would never go to Europe because he wished to use his money in a different way.</field>
    <field name="text">Why, then, was he loved by so many?</field>
    <field name="text">One of the New York papers gave this truthful answer:</field>
    <field name="text">"Peter Cooper went through his long life as gentle as a sweet woman, as kind as a good mother, as honest as a man could live, and remain human."</field>
    <field name="text">Some boys would be ashamed to be thought as gentle as a girl, but not so Peter Cooper.</field>
    <field name="text">He was born poor, and was always willing that everyone should know it.</field>
    <field name="text">He despised pride.</field>
    <field name="text">When his old horse and chaise came down Broadway, every cartman and omnibus driver turned aside for him.</field>
    <field name="text">Though a millionaire, he was their friend and brother, and they were proud and fond of him.</field>
    <field name="text">He gave away more than he kept.</field>
    <field name="text">He found places for the poor to work if possible.</field>
    <field name="text">He gave money to those he found were worthy.</field>
    <field name="text">And though he was one of the busiest men in America, he always took time to be kind.</field>
    <field name="text">His pastor, Mr. Collyer, said this of him:--</field>
    <field name="text">"His presence, wherever he went, lay like a bar of sunshine across a dark and troubled day. I have seen it light up the careworn faces of thousands of people. It seemed as if those who looked at him were saying to themselves; 'It cannot be so bad a world as we thought, since Peter Cooper lives in it and blesses us.'"</field>
    <field name="text">But how did this poor boy become a millionaire? And how did he get people to love him so?</field>
    <field name="text">He did it, boys and girls, by making up his mind to do it at first, and then sticking to it.</field>
    <field name="text">Nobody could have had more hard things to overcome than Peter Cooper.</field>
    <field name="text">His parents were poor and had nine children.</field>
    <field name="text">His father moved from town to town, always hoping to do better.</field>
    <field name="text">He forgot the old saying, "A rolling stone gathers no moss."</field>
    <field name="text">When the fifth baby was born, he was named after the Apostle Peter, because his father said, "This boy will come to something."</field>
    <field name="text">But he was not a strong boy.</field>
    <field name="text">He was able to go to school but one year of his life, and then only every other day.</field>
    <field name="text">His father was a hatter, and when Peter was eight years old he pulled hair from rabbit skins for hat pulp.</field>
    <field name="text">Year after year he worked harder than he was able, but he was determined to win.</field>
    <field name="text">When his eight little brothers and sisters needed shoes, he ripped up an old one to see how it was made. Always after that he made the shoes for the family.</field>
    <field name="text">Do you think a lazy boy would have done that?</field>
    <field name="text">When he was seventeen, he bade his anxious mother good-bye, and started for New York to make his fortune.</field>
    <field name="text">Do you know what a lottery is?</field>
    <field name="text">It is a way dishonest people have of making money.</field>
    <field name="text">Tickets are sold for prizes, and of course only one person can get the prize, while all the rest must lose their money.</field>
    <field name="text">Soon after Peter Cooper reached New York he saw an advertisement of a lottery.</field>
    <field name="text">He might draw a prize by buying a ticket.</field>
    <field name="text">Each ticket cost ten dollars.</field>
    <field name="text">Peter had just that much money.</field>
    <field name="text">He thought the matter over carefully.</field>
    <field name="text">He wished very much to have some money, for then he could help his mother.</field>
    <field name="text">So he bought a ticket, and drew--nothing.</field>
    <field name="text">Poor boy! he was now penniless.</field>
    <field name="text">But he never touched games of chance again.</field>
    <field name="text">Years afterward he used to say, "It was the cheapest piece of knowledge I ever bought."</field>
    <field name="text">Day after day the tall, slender boy walked the streets of New York looking for work.</field>
    <field name="text">At last he found a place.</field>
    <field name="text">It was in a carriage shop.</field>
    <field name="text">Here he bound himself as apprentice for five years at two dollars a month and board.</field>
    <field name="text">You see he could buy no good clothes.</field>
    <field name="text">He had no money for cigars or pleasures of any kind.</field>
    <field name="text">He helped to bring carriages for rich men's sons to ride in.</field>
    <field name="text">There is an old saying, that "everybody has to walk at one end of life," and they are fortunate who walk at the beginning and ride at the close.</field>
    <field name="text">When his day's work was over he liked to read.</field>
    <field name="text">His companions made fun of him because he would not join them.</field>
    <field name="text">He made a little money by extra work.</field>
    <field name="text">He hired a teacher, to whom he recited evenings.</field>
    <field name="text">He was often very tired, but he never complained.</field>
    <field name="text">He had many friends because he was always good-natured.</field>
    <field name="text">He used often to say to himself, "If ever I get rich I will build a place where the poor girls and boys of New York may have an education free."</field>
    <field name="text">Wasn't that a queer thought for a boy who earned only fifty cents a week?</field>
    <field name="text">Yet perhaps his even dreaming such dreams helped him to do the great things of which I shall tell you.</field>
    <field name="text">Now, Peter noticed that the tools which they worked with in the carriage shop were not very good.</field>
    <field name="text">So he began to try to make better ones.</field>
    <field name="text">He succeeded in doing so, but Mr. Woodward, the man for whom he worked, had all the benefit of his work.</field>
    <field name="text">But at last Peter's apprenticeship was over.</field>
    <field name="text">Much to his surprise Mr. Woodward one day called him into his office.</field>
    <field name="text">"You have been very faithful," he said, "and I will set you up in a carriage manufactory of your own.</field>
    <field name="text">"You could pay me back the money borrowed in a few years."</field>
    <field name="text">This was a remarkable offer for a poor young man.</field>
    <field name="text">But Peter had made it a solemn rule of his life never to go in debt.</field>
    <field name="text">So he thanked Mr. Woodward very earnestly, but declined his offer.</field>
    <field name="text">It was then Mr. Woodward's turn to be astonished.</field>
    <field name="text">But he knew Peter was right, and respected his good judgment in the matter.</field>
    <field name="text">We may now call Peter Cooper a mechanic.</field>
    <field name="text">A mechanic is one who has skill in using tools in shaping wood, metals, etc.</field>
    <field name="text">Peter now found a situation in a woolen mill at Hempstead, Long Island.</field>
    <field name="text">Here he received nine dollars a week.</field>
    <field name="text">Still he kept trying to find better ways of doing things.</field>
    <field name="text">He invented a machine for shearing cloth, and from that earned five hundred dollars in two years.</field>
    <field name="text">With so much money as this he could not rest until he had visited his mother.</field>
    <field name="text">He found his parents deeply in debt.</field>
    <field name="text">He gave them the whole of his money, and promised to do more than that.</field>
    <field name="text">His father had not made a mistake in naming him after the Apostle Peter.</field>
    <field name="text">During this time Mr. Cooper had learned to know a beautiful girl named Sarah Bedell. This girl became his wife.</field>
    <field name="text">They moved to New York.</field>
    <field name="text">Here Mr. Cooper had a grocery-store.</field>
    <field name="text">A friend advised him to buy a glue factory which was for sale.</field>
    <field name="text">He knew nothing of the business, but he thought he could learn it.</field>
    <field name="text">He soon made not only the best glue, but the cheapest in the country.</field>
    <field name="text">For thirty years he carried on this business almost alone, with no salesman and no book-keeper.</field>
    <field name="text">He rose every morning at daylight, kindled his factory fires, and worked all the forenoon making glue.</field>
    <field name="text">In the afternoon he sold it.</field>
    <field name="text">In the evenings he kept his accounts, wrote his letters, and read with his wife and children.</field>
    <field name="text">He worked this way long after he had an income of thirty thousand dollars a year.</field>
    <field name="text">This was not because he wanted to have so much more money for himself.</field>
    <field name="text">You remember he had a plan to carry out which would take much money.</field>
    <field name="text">That was to build his free school for the poor.</field>
    <field name="text">He had no time for parties or pleasures.</field>
    <field name="text">But the people of New York knew he was both honest and intelligent.</field>
    <field name="text">They asked him to be a member of the City Council, and President of their Board of Education.</field>
    <field name="text">Peter Cooper never refused to do anything which might help others.</field>
    <field name="text">So he did not refuse these offices.</field>
    <field name="text">I must tell you now about Mr. Cooper's first child, and how fine a thing it was to have an inventor for a papa.</field>
    <field name="text">Mr. Cooper made for this baby a self-rocking cradle, with a fan attached to keep off the flies, and with a musical instrument to soothe the dear baby into dreamland.</field>
    <field name="text">Mr. Cooper's business prospered.</field>
    <field name="text">[Illustration: THE "BEST FRIEND,"--FIRST LOCOMOTIVE BUILT IN   AMERICA. BUILT BY PETER COOPER.]</field>
    <field name="text">Once the glue factory burned, with a loss of forty thousand dollars.</field>
    <field name="text">But at nine o'clock the next morning there was lumber on the ground for a factory three times as large as the one burned.</field>
    <field name="text">He then built a rolling mill and furnace in Baltimore.</field>
    <field name="text">They were then trying to build the Baltimore and Ohio railroad.</field>
    <field name="text">Only thirteen miles of the road had been finished.</field>
    <field name="text">The directors were about to give up the work.</field>
    <field name="text">There were many sharp turns in the track.</field>
    <field name="text">The directors were discouraged because they thought no engine could be made to make those turns.</field>
    <field name="text">Mr. Cooper knew that this road would help his rolling mill.</field>
    <field name="text">Nothing could discourage him.</field>
    <field name="text">[Illustration: FIRST TRAIN IN AMERICA.]</field>
    <field name="text">He went to work and made the first locomotive made in America.</field>
    <field name="text">He attached a box-car to it.</field>
    <field name="text">Then he invited the directors to take a ride.</field>
    <field name="text">He took the place of engineer himself.</field>
    <field name="text">Away they flew over the thirteen miles in an hour.</field>
    <field name="text">The directors took courage, and the road was soon finished.</field>
    <field name="text">Years after, when Mr. Cooper had become a great man, he was invited to visit Baltimore.</field>
    <field name="text">The old engine was brought out, much to the delight of the people, who cheered again and again at sight of it.</field>
    <field name="text">Mr. Cooper soon built at Trenton, N.J., the largest rolling mill in the United States.</field>
    <field name="text">He also built a large blast furnace, and steel and wire works in different parts of Pennsylvania.</field>
    <field name="text">[Illustration: NEW YORK CENTRAL EMPIRE STATE EXPRESS. FASTEST   LOCOMOTIVE IN THE WORLD. "ENGINE 999."   Copyrighted by A.P. Yates, by permission of New York Central R.R.]</field>
    <field name="text">He bought the Andover iron mines.</field>
    <field name="text">He built eight miles of railroad in this rough country.</field>
    <field name="text">Over this road he carried forty thousand tons a year.</field>
    <field name="text">The poor boy, who once earned but twenty-five dollars a year, had become a millionaire.</field>
    <field name="text">No good luck accomplished this.</field>
    <field name="text">But these are the things that did it:</field>
    <field name="text">Hard work.     Living within his means.     Saving his time.     Common sense, which helped him to look carefully before he       invested his money.     Promptness.     Keeping his word.</field>
    <field name="text">Mr. Cooper was honorable in all his business.</field>
    <field name="text">Once he said to a friend who had an interest in the Trenton works:</field>
    <field name="text">"I do not feel quite easy about the amount we are making. We are making too much money. It is not right."</field>
    <field name="text">The price was made lower at once.</field>
    <field name="text">Do you not think Peter Cooper was an unusual kind of a man to lower the price of an article just because the world needed it so much?</field>
    <field name="text">He was now sixty-four years of age.</field>
    <field name="text">He had worked day and night for forty years to build his Free College.</field>
    <field name="text">He had bought the ground for it.</field>
    <field name="text">And now for five whole years he watched his great, six-story, brown-stone building as it grew.</field>
    <field name="text">The man who was once a penniless lad should teach many through these great stones some of the lessons he knew so well.</field>
    <field name="text">Some of these are industry, economy and perseverance.</field>
    <field name="text">The words which he wrote and placed in a box in the corner stone are not too hard for you to read.</field>
    <field name="text">"The great object that I desire to accomplish by the erection of this Institution is to open the avenues of scientific knowledge to the youth of our city and country, and so unfold the volume of Nature that the young may see the beauties of creation, enjoy its blessings, and learn to love the Author from whom cometh every good and perfect gift."</field>
    <field name="text">But would the poor young men and women of New York who worked hard all day care for an education?</field>
    <field name="text">Some people said no.</field>
    <field name="text">But Mr. Cooper thought of his own boyhood, and believed that young people loved books, and would be glad of a chance to study them.</field>
    <field name="text">[Illustration: COOPER INSTITUTE, NEW YORK CITY.]</field>
    <field name="text">And when the grand building was opened students crowded in from the shops and factories.</field>
    <field name="text">Some were worn and tired, as Peter Cooper had often been in his youth.</field>
    <field name="text">But they studied eagerly in spite of that.</field>
    <field name="text">Every Saturday night two thousand came together in the great hall.</field>
    <field name="text">There the most famous people in the world lectured before them.</field>
    <field name="text">Every year nearly five hundred thousand read in the free library and reading rooms.</field>
    <field name="text">Four thousand pupils came to the night school to study science and art.</field>
    <field name="text">The white-haired, kindly-faced man went daily to see the students.</field>
    <field name="text">They loved him as a father.</field>
    <field name="text">His last act was to buy ten type-writers for the girls in that department.</field>
    <field name="text">Has the work paid?</field>
    <field name="text">Ask any of those young men and women who have gone out from Cooper Institute to earn their own living.</field>
    <field name="text">Not one of them had to pay a cent for his education.</field>
    <field name="text">No one is admitted who does not expect to earn his living.</field>
    <field name="text">Mr. Cooper did not love weak, idle young people, who are willing their parents shall take care of them.</field>
    <field name="text">The work has grown so large that more money is needed--perhaps another million.</field>
    <field name="text">Mr. Cooper gave it two millions of dollars.</field>
    <field name="text">Many are turned from the doors because there is no more room.</field>
    <field name="text">Some of the pupils from the Institute have become teachers.</field>
    <field name="text">One receives two dollars an hour for teaching.</field>
    <field name="text">Several engrave on wood.</field>
    <field name="text">One receives one hundred and fifty dollars a month.</field>
    <field name="text">Another, a lady, married a gentleman of wealth, and to show her gratitude to Mr. Cooper has opened another "Free School of Art."</field>
    <field name="text">Is it any wonder that when Peter Cooper died thirty-five hundred came up from the Institution to lay roses upon his coffin.</field>
    <field name="text">His last words to his son and daughter were not to forget Cooper Union.</field>
    <field name="text">They have just given one hundred thousand dollars to it.</field>
    <field name="text">Mr. Cooper had many friends among the great and good of the land.</field>
    <field name="text">He died as unselfishly as he had lived, and who can measure the good he did in the world?</field>
    <field name="text">[Illustration: EDISON.]</field>
  </doc>
</add>
